<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!--   This file is part of the documentation of PreTeXt      -->
<!--                                                          -->
<!--      PreTeXt Author's Guide                              -->
<!--                                                          -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 2013-2016  Robert A. Beezer                -->
<!-- See the file COPYING for copying conditions.             -->

<chapter xml:id="add-ons">
    <title>(*) Add-Ons</title>

    <introduction>
        <p>Some features of the <init>HTML</init> version of a document rely on third-party services.  Once an author configures them, then <pretext /> will do the rest for you.  This chapter provides guidance on the configuration processes. </p>
    </introduction>

    <section xml:id="add-on-analytics">
        <title>(*) Analytics</title>
        <p></p>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="add-on-search">
        <title>Search</title>

        <p>Search facilities are enabled through <url href="https://cse.google.com/cse">Google Custom Search Engine</url><idx>Google Custom Search Engine</idx>.  Please, please report any discrepancies in the following instructions as the setup interface at Google changes out from underneath us.  These instructions are accurate as of 2016-12-12.</p>

        <p>Besides being useful for search facilities, setting up a search engine might be a good way to alert Google of something newly available, and initiate your book's rise up the search results rankings.</p>

        <list>
            <caption>Configuring Google Custom Search</caption>

            <ol>
                <li><p>Create an account with Google (GMail, YouTube, <etc />) and make sure you are signed in.</p></li>

                <li><p>Visit <url href="https://cse.google.com/cse">GCSE</url> and <c>Add</c> a new search engine of follow <c>New Search Engine</c>.</p></li>

                <li><p>Provide a <init>URL</init> for the top-level domain name/directory for your book/document.  Everything below this will be indexed.  We have taken some care to mark knowl content in a way compatible with the search facility, but there is more work to do here.</p></li>

                <li><p>Give the engine a GCSE-specific name, so you can tell later which one it is when you have several.</p></li>

                <li><p>Under <c>Edit Search Engine > Setup > Basics > Details > Search engine ID</c> find a string which uniquely identifies your new search engine.  Save this, you'll need to make it part of your <init>MBX</init> document.</p></li>

                <li><p>Under <c>Edit Search Engine > Setup > Admin</c> add co-authors or trusted backup personnel.</p></li>

                <li><p>Under <c>Edit Search Engine > Business > Settings</c> set your <c>Advertising status</c> to the non-profit setting if you qualify (most universties should).</p></li>

                <li><p>Fiddle with <c>Edit Search Engine > Look and Feel</c> at your own risk!  Only the defaults are tested and supported.</p></li>

                <li><p><c>Edit Search Engine > Setup > Indexing</c> sends you to Google Search Console to see if your book is already being indexed.  YOu may need to go through a confirmation process to establish that you are the owner of the website being indexed.  If you see taht your book is not yet being indexed, you may want to wait as long as a week before your material does get indexed and you make a search box available.</p></li>
            </ol>
        </list>

        <list>
            <caption>Configuring <pretext /> for Google Search</caption>

            <ol>
                <li><p>The <c>Search engine ID</c> you saved from above is referenced in Google's code as a <c>cx</c> number.  Add an element in your MBX source as <c>docinfo/search/google/cx</c> with the value of your book's ID as the content.  See the sample article for a working example to mimic.</p></li>

                <li><p>The <c>cx</c> element will alert the <pretext /> conversion and fully enable and implement search.  You're done, and everything should just work.  You should see a Google-branded search box to the top right of each of your pages.  (We have no control over the branding.)</p></li>

                <li><p>Time to rebuild your official <init>HTML</init> output and make the improved version available.</p></li>
            </ol>
        </list>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="add-on-annotation">
        <title>(*) Annotation</title>
        <p></p>
    </section>


</chapter>
