<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!--   This file is part of the documentation of PreTeXt      -->
<!--                                                          -->
<!--      PreTeXt Author's Guide                              -->
<!--                                                          -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 2013-2016  Robert A. Beezer                -->
<!-- See the file COPYING for copying conditions.             -->

<chapter xml:id="conversions">
    <title>Conversions</title>

    <introduction>
        <p>A main goal of <pretext /> is to provide a language for describing a scholarly document by its structure, with contained content, and with no description of the presentation.  It then becomes possible to use software to produce different formats, where the presentation takes advantage of that format and enhances the meaning of the content through the expression of the structure.</p>

        <p>But different output formats have different capabilities.  For example, a conversion to <init>HTML</init> can take advantage of knowls to organize smaller chunks of content, while a conversion to <init>PDF</init> can take advantage of page numbers for cross-references.  And in these two examples, the capability of the one output format is mostly impossible or silly in the other.  Look here for notes that are independent of the <pretext /> vocabulary, and specific to the format produced by a conversion.</p>

    </introduction>

    <section xml:id="processing-parameters">
        <title>Processing Parameters</title>

        <p>Many of the options for different conversions are accomplished by command-line options, which are fed to <c>xsltproc</c> by what that program calls <term>string parameters</term>.  Here are two examples:<cd>
            <cline>xsltproc -stringparam html.knowl.example no mathbook-html.xsl fauna.xml</cline>
            <cline>xsltproc -stringparam latex.font.size 14pt mathbook-latex.xsl fauna.xml</cline>
        </cd>The first will make <tag>element</tag> content render on a page, rather than hidden in a knowl, which is the default for a conversion to <init>HTML</init>.  And the second will use a larger overall font size, while trying to preserve the same number of characters per line (with consequent smaller margins).</p>

        <p>Notice that these two examples do nothing to change the <em>words</em> that a conversion produces, which is why you do not specify them in your source.  They are conversion options that do not affect your content in significant ways, and are related to the particular output format.</p>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="conversion-html">
        <title>Conversions to <init>HTML</init></title>

        <paragraphs>
            <title>Knowled Content</title>

            <p>We knowl examples, proofs, and inline exercises by default, mostly so a new author knows that presentation is an option.  The knowlization of items can be controlled by a variety of command-line processing parameters (<xref ref="processing-parameters" />).  While these are in flux, we do not list them here, but instead suggest you open <c>xsl/mathbook-html.xsl</c> and search on <c>html.knowl</c> to see what is available.</p>

            <p>Note that some of these switches are for broad categories of items, for example, <c>html.knowl.theorem</c> will also knowl <tag>lemma</tag>s, <tag>corollary</tag>s, <tag>fact</tag>s, and more.  This choice applies document-wide, there is no plan to support electing this on a case-by-case basis.</p>
        </paragraphs>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="conversion-latex">
        <title>Conversions to <latex /></title>

        <p>Similar to the case for <init>HTML</init> conversion (<xref ref="conversion-html" />) there is a variety of command-line processing parameters available (<xref ref="processing-parameters" />).  Until we are ready to document these carefully, open <c>xsl/mathbook-latex.xsl</c> and poke around to see what is available.</p>
    </section>
</chapter>
