<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- This file is part of the documentation of MathBook XML   -->
<!--                                                          -->
<!--    MathBook XML Author's Guide                           -->
<!--                                                          -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 2013-2016  Robert A. Beezer                -->
<!-- See the file COPYING for copying conditions.             -->

<chapter xml:id="mbx-script">
    <title>The <c>mbx</c> Script</title>

    <introduction>
        <p>XSL is a very powerful language for text processing.  However, it cannot do everything.  The <c>mbx</c> script is a Swiss Army Knife of sorts to operate on parts of your document and manage processing that requires the application of external programs, such as <latex /> and Sage.</p>
    </introduction>

    <section>
        <title>(*) Rough Quickstart</title>

        <p>Some quick preliminary hints.  This section <em>will</em> be expanded.</p>

        <ul>
            <li><p><c>mbx -h</c>:  help message, command summary</p></li>
            <li><p><c>mbx -v</c>:  progress indicators (verbose)</p></li>
            <li><p><c>mbx -vv</c>: debugging information (doubly-verbose)</p></li>
            <li><p>Provide complete debugging output with bug reports</p></li>
        </ul>

        <p>Much like the build advice at the end of <xref ref="processing-file-management" />, the <c>mbx</c> script collects necessary bits into a system-created temporary directory, does its work, and copies out the desired results.  Some insight into failures can be found in this directory (which we leave behind for the system to clean-up later).  Early in the <c>-vv</c> doubly-verbose output, this directory is reported after the string <c>temporary directory:</c>.</p>

        <p>An example:</p>

        <console>
            <prompt>$ </prompt>
            <input>~/mathbook/script/mbx -vv -c sageplot -f svg -d images ~/mathbook/examples/sample-article/sample-article.xml</input>
        </console>

        <p>This will extract every image described in <c>sample-article</c> by a <tag>sageplot</tag> element and produce output as SVG files (if possible), which will be deposited in the <c>images</c> subdirectory of the current working directory.</p>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Restricting the Scope</title>

        <p>The <c>-r</c> (<c>--restrict</c>) switch deserves special mention.  It is followed by the value of an <attribute>xml:id</attribute> attribute present in your source XML file.  Then whatever action the script is asked to perform, it will only act on a subtree of the hierarchy, rooted at the element with the given <attribute>xml:id</attribute> value.</p>

        <p>So if your images are complex or numerous (or both!) and take a long time to process, you can restrict attention to whatever part of the document you are actively editing, and you can even restrict to a single <tag>image</tag> and so produce just a single graphics file.</p>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="section-mbx-on-windows">
        <title><c>mbx</c> on Windows</title>
        <p>Making the <c>mbx</c> script Windows-compatible is an ongoing project. It is possible you may find a bug, which we would ask that you report. In addition, if you have followed the directions in <xref ref="windows-install-notes" />, then you may need to customize the <c>mbx.cfg</c> configuration file, which tells <c>mbx</c> where to find the helper programs it relies on. See below for the details.</p>
        <p>The script uses a <latex /> utility called <c>pdfcrop</c> to, well, crop PDF images generated by a <latex /> engine. This utility has not been made to work in the Windows CMD shell. If you want to generate images on Windows, you should use the Git Bash shell as described in <xref ref="installing-git" />.</p>
        <ol>
            <li>
                <p>Copy the file <cd>/path/to/mathbook/script/mbx.cfg</cd> to <cd>/path/to/mathbook/user/mbx.cfg</cd></p>
            </li>
            <li>
                <p>Replace the right-hand sides of the entries for <c>pdfsvg</c> and <c>pdfpng</c> with the full path name of the <c>convert</c> utility installed with ImageMagick (<xref ref="installing-imagemagick" />), <alert>using forward slashes</alert>. It will be something like <cd>c:/ImageMagick-7.0.1-Q16/convert.exe</cd></p>
            </li>
        </ol>
    </section>

    <!--
    <section xml:id="processing-">
        <title>(*) </title>

    </section>

   -->


</chapter>
