<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!--   This file is part of the documentation of PreTeXt      -->
<!--                                                          -->
<!--      PreTeXt Author's Guide                              -->
<!--                                                          -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 2013-2016  Robert A. Beezer                -->
<!-- See the file COPYING for copying conditions.             -->

<chapter xml:id="webwork">
    <title><webwork /> Automated Homework Problems</title>
    <author>Alex Jordan</author>

    <introduction>
        <p>With a <webwork/> server (version 2.14 or higher, or <url href="https://webwork-ptx.aimath.org"><c>webwork-ptx.aimath.org</c></url>) and a little setup work, you can embed <webwork/> exercises<idx><h><webwork/></h><h><webwork/> exercise</h></idx> in your <pretext/> project. HTML output can have interactive problem cells or print problems in <q>static</q> form. PDF output will print static versions. And all such exercises can be archived into a file tree to be uploaded onto a <webwork/> server for use in the <q>traditional</q> way.</p>

        <p>See the <pretext/> Publishing Guide for how to configure a <webwork/> course and server to process your <webwork/> problems, and then how to process them.</p>
    </introduction>

    <section xml:id="webwork-source">
        <title><webwork/> Problems</title>

        <introduction>
            <p>A <tag>webwork</tag><idx><webwork /></idx> tag must be inside an <tag>exercise</tag>, <em>optionally</em> preceded by an <tag>introduction</tag>, and <em>optionally</em> followed by a <tag>conclusion</tag>.</p>
            <pre>
            <![CDATA[
            <exercise>
                <introduction>
                </introduction>

                <webwork>
                </webwork>

                <conclusion>
                </conclusion>
            </exercise>
            ]]>
            </pre>
            <p>There are several methods for putting content into the <tag>webwork</tag>. (Note that an empty <tag>webwork</tag> with no attributes will simply produce the camelcase <webwork/> logo.)</p>
        </introduction>

        <subsection>
            <title>Using an Existing <webwork/> Problem</title>
            <p>
                If a problem already exists and is accessible from the hosting course's <c>templates/</c> folder, then you can simply include it as a <attr>source</attr> attribute. For example if it is a problem in the Open Problem Library (OPL), then relative to the <c>templates/</c> folder, its path is <c>Library/...</c> and you may use:

                <cd>&lt;webwork source="Library/PCC/BasicAlgebra/Exponents/exponentsMultiplication0.pg" /></cd>

                Or if you have a problem's PG file, you can upload it into the hosting course's <c>templates/local/</c> folder and use it with:

                <cd>&lt;webwork source="local/my_problem.pg" /></cd>
            </p>
        </subsection>

        <subsection>
            <title>Perl-free Problems</title>
            <p>If you'd just like to rattle off a quick question with no randomization, you can do as in this example:</p>
            <pre>
            <![CDATA[
            <exercise>
                <webwork>
                    <statement>
                        <p><m>1+2=</m><var name="'3'" width="5" /></p>
                    </statement>
                </webwork>
            </exercise>
            ]]>
            </pre>

            <p>The <tag>exercise</tag> above could be given an optional <tag>title</tag>, <tag>introduction</tag>, and <tag>conclusion</tag>. The <tag>webwork</tag> inside could be given a <tag>hint</tag> and <tag>solution</tag>. These are discussed in <xref ref="webwork-pg-code">Subsection</xref>.</p>

            <p>In the above example, <c>'3'</c> is the <attr>name</attr> attribute to a <tag>var</tag> element. This is how to create an answer blank that is expecting <m>3</m> as the answer. What you give as a <attr>name</attr> attribute will be passed to PG's <c>Compute()</c> command, so it needs to be valid input for <c>Compute()</c>. Note that you could pass a string encased in quotes, or a perl expression. Just be mindful of the difference:<ul>
                <li>
                    <p><c>8**2</c> will process a perl real using exponentiation and lead to the MathObject Real 64.</p>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <p><c>'8^2'</c> will process a perl string and lead to the MathObject Real 64.</p>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <p><c>8^2</c> will process the perl real using bitwise XOR and lead to the MathObject Real 10.</p>
                </li>
            </ul></p>

            <p>The default context is <c>Numeric</c>, which understands numerical expressions and formulaic expressions in the variable <m>x</m>. You can activate some other context as in this example:</p>
            <pre>
            <![CDATA[
            <exercise>
                <webwork>
                    <setup>
                        <pg-code>
                            Context("ImplicitPlane");
                        </pg-code>
                    </setup>
                    <statement>
                        <p>The answer is <m>x+y=1</m>.</p>
                        <p><var name="'x+y=1'" width="8" /></p>
                    </statement>
                </webwork>
            </exercise>
            ]]>
            </pre>

            <p>Many special contexts are automatically detected by <pretext/>, and it loads the appropriate macro file into the PG problem. However you may need to explicitly load a macro file as described in <xref ref="webwork-pg-code">Subsection</xref>.</p>

        </subsection>

        <subsection xml:id="webwork-pg-code">
            <title>PG code in Problems</title>
            <p>To have randomization in problems or otherwise take advantage of the algorithmic programming capabilities of Perl and <webwork/>'s PG language requires using a <tag>setup</tag> tag. Having at least a little familiarity with coding problems in <webwork/> is necessary, although for simpler problems you could get away with mimicking the sample article in <c>mathbook/examples/webwork/</c>. A <tag>statement</tag>, <em>optional</em> <tag>hint</tag>, and <em>optional</em> <tag>solution</tag> follow.</p>
            <pre>
            <![CDATA[
            <webwork>

                <setup>
                </setup>

                <statement>
                </statement>

                <hint>
                </hint>

                <solution>
                </solution>

            </webwork>
            ]]>
            </pre>

            <p>The <tag>setup</tag> contains a <tag>pg-code</tag>. If you are familiar with code for <webwork/> PG problems, the <tag>pg-code</tag> contains lines of PG code that would appear in the <q>setup</q> portion of the problem. Typically, this is the code that follows <c>TEXT(beginproblem());</c> and precedes the first <c>BEGIN_TEXT</c> or <c>BEGIN_PGML</c>. If your code needs any special <webwork/> macro libraries, you may load them in a <tag>pg-macros</tag> tag prior to <tag>setup</tag>, with each such <c>.pl</c> file's name inside a <tag>macro-file</tag> tag. However many of the most common macro libraries will be loaded automatically based on the content and attributes you use in the rest of your problem.</p>

            <p>Here is a small example. Following the example, we'll continue discussing <tag>statement</tag> and <tag>solution</tag>.</p>
            <pre>
            <![CDATA[
            <webwork>
                <setup>
                    <pg-code>
                        Context("LimitedNumeric");
                        $a = Compute(random(1, 9, 1));
                        $b = Compute(random(1, 9, 1));
                        $c = $a + $b;
                    </pg-code>
                </setup>

                <statement>
                    <p>Compute <m><var name="$a"/> + <var name="$b"/></m>.</p>
                    <instruction>Type your answer without using the <c>+</c> sign.</instruction>
                    <p>The sum is <var name="$c" width="2"/>.</p>
                </statement>

                <solution>
                    <p><m><var name="$a"/> + <var name="$b"/> = <var name="$c"/></m>.</p>
                </solution>
            </webwork>
            ]]>
            </pre>

            <p>Within a <tag>statement</tag>, <tag>hint</tag>, or <tag>solution</tag>, reference <tag>var</tag> tags by <attr>name</attr>.</p>

            <p>Within the <tag>statement</tag>, a <tag>var</tag> tag with either a <attr>width</attr> or <attr>form</attr> attribute creates an input field. The <attr>name</attr> attribute declares what the answer will be.</p>

            <p>A <tag>var</tag> can have <attr>form="essay"</attr>, in which case it need not have a <attr>name</attr> attribute. This is for open-ended questions that must be graded by a human. The form field will be an expandable input block if the question is served to an authenticated user within <webwork/>. But for the <webwork/> cells in PTX HTML output, there will just be a message explaining that there is no place to enter an answer.</p>

            <p>A <tag>var</tag> can have <attr>form="array"</attr>. You would use this when the answer is a Matrix or Vector MathObject (a <webwork/> classification) to cause the input form to be an array of smaller fields instead of one big field.</p>

            <p>A <tag>var</tag> can have <attr>form="popup"</attr> or <attr>form="buttons"</attr> for multiple choice questions.</p>

            <p>If you are familiar with PG, then in your <tag>pg-code</tag> you might write a custom evaluator (a combination of a custom answer checker, post filters, pre filters, <etc/>). If you store this similar to
            <cd>$my_evaluator = $answer -> cmp(...);</cd>
            then the <tag>var</tag> can have <attr>evaluator="$my_evaluator"</attr>.</p>

            <p>An <tag>instruction</tag> is specific instructions for how the reader might type or otherwise electronically submit their answer. Contents of an <tag>instruction</tag> will be omitted from print and other static output forms. The <tag>instruction</tag> is a peer to <tag>p</tag>, but may only contain <q>short text</q> children.</p>

            <p>Some general information on authoring <webwork/> problems can be found in a <url href="http://webwork.maa.org/wiki/Problem_Authoring_Videos">set of videos at <c>webwork.maa.org/wiki/Problem_Authoring_Videos</c></url>.
            Not all of this is relevant to authoring within <pretext/> but there are parts that will be helpful for constructing the Perl code necessary for randomized problems.</p>

        </subsection>

        <subsection>
            <title>Reusing a <tag>webwork</tag> by <attr>xml:id</attr></title>
            <p>Planned.</p>
        </subsection>

    </section>

</chapter>
