<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!--   This file is part of the documentation of PreTeXt      -->
<!--                                                          -->
<!--      PreTeXt Publisher's Guide                           -->
<!--                                                          -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 2013-2017  Robert A. Beezer, David Farmer  -->
<!-- See the file COPYING for copying conditions.             -->

<chapter xml:id="online-html">
    <title>Conversion to Online HTML</title>

    <introduction>
        <p>Similar to the case for <latex /> conversion (<xref ref="pdf-print"/>) there is a variety of command-line processing parameters available (<xref ref="processing-parameters" />).  Until we are ready to document these carefully, open <c>xsl/mathbook-html.xsl</c> and poke around to see what is available.</p>
    </introduction>

    <section xml:id="knowled-content">
        <title>Knowled Content</title>

        <p>We knowl examples, proofs, and inline exercises by default, mostly so a new author discovers that this presentation is an option.  The knowlization of items can be controlled by a variety of command-line processing parameters (<xref ref="processing-parameters" />).  While these are in flux, we do not list them here, but instead suggest you open <c>xsl/mathbook-html.xsl</c> and search on <c>html.knowl</c> to see what is available.</p>

        <p>Note that some of these switches are for broad categories of items, for example, <c>html.knowl.theorem</c> will also knowl <tag>lemma</tag>s, <tag>corollary</tag>s, <tag>fact</tag>s, and more.  This choice applies document-wide, there is no plan to support electing this on a case-by-case basis.</p>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Lists</title>

        <p>On a description list (<tag>dl</tag>), only <attr>width</attr> values of <c>narrow</c> and <c>medium</c> are implemented. (2018-03-28)</p>

        <p>Lists with several columns are rendered in row-major order, as of 2018-02-28.  In other words, the first list items (<tag>li</tag>) in your source will populate the first row.</p>

    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Styling</title>

        <introduction>
            <p>The PreTeXt conversion to <init>HTML</init> creates standard <init>HTML</init> elements, with styles controlled by <init>CSS</init> via class names (and not so much via the element names).  As evidence of this, building <init>HTML</init> without the accompanying Javascript and <init>CSS</init> renders in a readable fashion, albeit quite plain (as one would expect).  This section describes ways that a publisher can influence the style.</p>
        </introduction>

        <subsection>
            <title>Colors</title>

            <p>The processing parameter <c>html.css.colorfile</c> can be provided as the name of a file describing a color theme for <init>HTML</init> output.  It presumes the same server which serves the remainder of the <init>CSS</init> (<c>pretextbook.org</c> by default).  So for example,<cd>
                <cline>-stringparam html.css.colorfile colors_pastel_blue_orange.css</cline>
            </cd>will provide a softer look.  The default colors are contained in <c>colors_default.css</c>.  It is easy to inspect and compare these files to see what is involved in designing a color theme.  In particular, <c>colors_default.css</c> contains documentation on how to design a theme.</p>
        </subsection>
    </section>
</chapter>
