<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!--   This file is part of the documentation of PreTeXt      -->
<!--                                                          -->
<!--      PreTeXt Publisher's Guide                           -->
<!--                                                          -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 2013-2017  Robert A. Beezer, David Farmer  -->
<!-- See the file COPYING for copying conditions.             -->

<chapter xml:id="pdf-print">
    <title>Conversion to PDF and Print</title>

    <p>
        <idx><h>PDF</h><h>electronic</h></idx>
        <idx><h>PDF</h><h>print</h></idx>
        The stylesheet <c>mathbook-latex.xsl</c> can produce two very similar outputs.  Each is a file in <latex/> syntax, which can be converted to a <init>PDF</init> with a <latex/> executable (<q>engine</q>).  However, there are two purposes for such a <init>PDF</init>.  The first is a document which is meant to be read on a screen.  We call this an <term>electronic <init>PDF</init></term>.  The second is meant to be printed as a physical book, so it would be the file you provide to a copy shop, campus bookstore, or print-on-demand service (see <xref ref="print-on-demand"/>).  We call this a <term>print <init>PDF</init></term>.
    </p>

    <p>As an illustration of the difference, an electronic <init>PDF</init> will contain cross-references that are active, and colored to be obvious to the reader.  For the print <init>PDF</init> the same cross-reference will be black and inactive.</p>

    <p>The <c>latex.print</c> switch controls the selection of the two output modes of this single stylesheet.  The default is <c>no</c> for the electronic version, and <c>yes</c> will change to the print version.  In this chapter, we describe both of these two, slightly dissimilar, conversions together.</p>

    <paragraphs>
        <title>Text Justification and Alignment</title>

        <p>The <c>text.alignment</c> switch will control how text is aligned (such as in paragraphs).  The value <c>justify</c> is the default, and <c>raggedright</c> will cause alignment on the left, with an uneven right edge, employing less hypenation.</p>
    </paragraphs>

    <paragraphs>
        <title>One-Sided or Two-Sided</title>

        <p>An electronic <init>PDF</init> will default to page layout appropriate for a document printed single-sided, which makes the most sense for a document that may not be printed, or which might be printed on a personal printer.</p>

        <p>A print <init>PDF</init> will default to page layout appropriate for a document printed two-sided, which makes the most sense for a document that may be sent to a print-on-demand service or printed on a printer that will print on both sides of a sheet of paper.</p>

        <p>These defaults may be overridden with the <c>latex.sided</c> switch with values <c>one</c> and <c>two</c>.</p>

        <p>One-sided layout will default to symmetric left/right margins, and page headers with the page numbers <em>always</em> placed in the upper-right corner as part of default page headers.  There will be no blank pages between chapters of a book.</p>

        <p>Two-sided layout will have asymmetric margins with the ratio of inner (adjacent to spine) to outer at <c>2:3</c>.  You need some extra space at the spine to compensate for the binding, but when a book is open, the two pages are separated by two inner margins, so these do not need to be as wide as the outer margin to give some distance between the pages.  And readers will want more space to write in the outer margins, perhaps providing simple proofs of important results.  (This ratio may be changed with the <c>hmarginratio</c> key of the <c>geometry</c> package.)  Page headings will have page numbers on the outside of the page, with odd numbers on the right-side page.  Chapters will possibly have a blank page between them, so they begin on a right/odd page.  Behavior is similar in the front matter and back matter.</p>
    </paragraphs>

    <paragraphs>
        <title>Page Shape</title>

        <p>The <c>latex.geometry</c> switch can be used to supply a single string composed of any options to the <c>\geometry{}</c> command of the <latex/> <c>geometry</c> package, and these will override any defaults supplied by <pretext/>.  Resist the temptation to pack in as much text on the page as you can.  <pretext/> varies the width of the text in reaction to the font size and is already very close to the maximum number of characters per line for comfortable reading by humans.</p>

        <p>An electronic <init>PDF</init> may be printed on physical paper, but perhaps you want to make a version that works well on a portable device that naturally supports a portrait orientation, such as an Android tablet, an iPad, a Kindle (device or application), smart phone, Sony Digital Paper, or a ReMarkable tablet.  Aspect ratios vary across these devices, but once you settle on a target ratio, we have had good luck with the following algorithm and parameters:<ol>
            <li>Specify 10 point text</li>
            <li>Text width of about 4.5 inches</li>
            <li>Add quarter-inch left/right margins to compute text width</li>
            <li>Use aspect ratio to compute an overall height (about 6.5 inches)</li>
            <li>Subtract quarter-inch top and bottom margins to obtain text height</li>
        </ol>Then you can provide the <c>geometry</c> package the overall size as the <c>papersize</c> and the text width and text height as the <c>total</c> size of the body, resulting in equal (tight) margins all around, and good use of limited screen real estate.  These parameters create a <init>PDF</init> that is very legible on a larger smart phone, and for fine detail, rotating the device to landscape works well.  Really.</p>
    </paragraphs>

    <paragraphs>
        <title>Nested Lists</title>

        <p><latex /> can fail if lists are nested too deeply.  Maximums may be up to four nested ordered lists, and up to six overall (mixing in unordered lists).  If you hit these limits, ask yourself if your situation is really that complicated, or ask us to consider a feature request adding a technical fix.</p>
    </paragraphs>

    <paragraphs>
        <title>Multi-Column List Order</title>

        <p>Lists with several columns are rendered in column-major order, as of 2018-02-28.  In other words, the first list items (<tag>li</tag>) in your source will populate the first column.</p>
    </paragraphs>

    <paragraphs>
        <title>Watermarks</title>

        <p>You can add a watermark to your <ini>PDF</ini> which will render as large, light grey text, at an angle across teh page.  Use <c>latex.watermark</c> to set the text (avoid obscure characters or symbols, and do not use any <init>XML</init> markup).  Use <c>latex.watermark.scale</c> to adjust for long or short text.  The <latex/>-only <q>\\</q> will survive in the text to create multiple lines of text.  Submit a feature request if this is not flexible enough to meet a special need.</p>
    </paragraphs>

    <paragraphs>
        <title>Fill-Ins</title>

        <p>The <tag>fillin</tag> element can be rendered as a line near the baseline of the current line of text, or as a complete rectangle (<q>box</q>).  Set <c>latex.fillin.style</c> to the values <c>underline</c> or <c>box</c>.</p>
    </paragraphs>

    <paragraphs>
        <title>Experimentation</title>

        <p>Two hooks are provided to allow for arbitrary additions to the <latex/> preamble.  It should go without saying that this is for experimenting with new features and is no way supported, including, but not limited to, interactions with current <latex/> packages in use, or those added in the future.</p>

        <p>Arbitrary text (<latex/>) used as the values of <c>latex.preamble.early</c> and <c>latex.preamble.late</c> will be added to the very beginning, or very end (respectively), of the generated preamble.</p>
    </paragraphs>

    <paragraphs>
        <title>Switch Reference</title>

        <p>The following switches can be provided on the command-line, or perhaps more conveniently in a simple <init>XSL</init> file.</p>

        <table>
            <caption>Options for <latex/> Conversion</caption>

            <tabular>
                <row bottom="medium">
                    <cell>Switch</cell>
                    <cell>Default</cell>
                    <cell>Values</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell><c>latex.print</c></cell>
                    <cell><c>no</c></cell>
                    <cell><c>yes</c>, <c>no</c></cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell><c>latex.sides</c></cell>
                    <cell>Varies</cell>
                    <cell><c>one</c>, <c>two</c></cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell><c>latex.font.size</c></cell>
                    <cell><c>10pt</c></cell>
                    <cell><c>8pt</c> to <c>20pt</c> (8 steps)</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell><c>latex.geometry</c></cell>
                    <cell></cell>
                    <cell>Any options to <c>\geometry{}</c></cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell><c>text.alignment</c></cell>
                    <cell><c>justify</c></cell>
                    <cell><c>raggedright</c>, <c>justify</c></cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell><c>latex.watermark</c></cell>
                    <cell></cell>
                    <cell>Simple text, no markup</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell><c>latex.watermark.scale</c></cell>
                    <cell><c>2.0</c></cell>
                    <cell>Positive rational number</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell><c>latex.fillin.style</c></cell>
                    <cell><c>underline</c></cell>
                    <cell><c>underline</c>, <c>box</c></cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell><c>latex.preamble.early</c></cell>
                    <cell></cell>
                    <cell>Arbitrary <latex/></cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell><c>latex.preamble.late</c></cell>
                    <cell></cell>
                    <cell>Arbitrary <latex/></cell>
                </row>
            </tabular>
        </table>
    </paragraphs>
</chapter>
