<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!--   This file is part of the documentation of PreTeXt      -->
<!--                                                          -->
<!--      PreTeXt Author's Guide                              -->
<!--                                                          -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 2013-2016  Robert A. Beezer                -->
<!-- See the file COPYING for copying conditions.             -->

<chapter xml:id="webwork">
    <title><webwork /> Automated Homework Problems</title>
    <author>Alex Jordan</author>

    <introduction>
        <p>With a <webwork/> server (version 2.14 or higher, or <url href="https://webwork-ptx.aimath.org"><c>webwork-ptx.aimath.org</c></url>) and a little setup work, you can embed <webwork/> exercises<idx><h><webwork/></h><h><webwork/> exercise</h></idx> in your <pretext/> project. HTML output can have interactive problem cells or print problems in <q>static</q> form. PDF output will print static versions. And all such exercises can be archived into a file tree to be uploaded onto a <webwork/> server for use in the <q>traditional</q> way.</p>

        <p>See the <pretext/> Authoring Guide for how to include <webwork/> problems in your source.</p>
    </introduction>

    <section xml:id="webwork-configuration">
        <title>Configuring a <webwork/> Course for <pretext/></title>
        <p>We assume a mild familiarity with administrating a <webwork/> server. The version of <webwork/> needs to be 2.14 or later for use with <pretext/>. Using the <c>admin</c> course, create a course named <c>anonymous</c>. (You could name it something else, but we assume the name is <c>anonymous</c> in this guide.) In the course's Course Configuration menu, set all permissions to <c>admin</c> (or perhaps set some to the even more restrictive <c>nobody</c>). Except set <q>Allowed to login to the course</q> to <c>login_proctor</c>.</p>
        <p>In the Classlist Editor, add a user named <c>anonymous</c> (again, you could use some other name), and set that user's permission level to <c>login_proctor</c>, the permission level one higher than <c>student</c>. Set that user's password to <c>anonymous</c> (again, you could use some other password). Note that because this is public information, anyone will be able to log into this course as this user. This is why setting the permissions earlier is very important. (Especially preventing this user from changing its own password.)</p>
        <p>Add the following lines to the <c>course.conf</c> file (which lives in the parent folder of the <c>templates/</c> folder.)</p>
        <pre>
        # Hide message about previewing hints and solutions for instructors
        $pg{specialPGEnvironmentVars}{ALWAYS_SHOW_HINT_PERMISSION_LEVEL} = 100;
        $pg{specialPGEnvironmentVars}{ALWAYS_SHOW_SOLUTION_PERMISSION_LEVEL} = 100;
        </pre>
        <p>In the <c>templates/macros/</c> folder, edit <c>PGcourse.pl</c> (or create it if need be) and add the lines:</p>
        <pre>
        #### Replace essay boxes with a message
        sub essay_box {
            my $out = MODES(
                TeX => '',
                Latex2HTML => '',
                HTML => qq!&lt;P>
                    If you were logged into a WeBWorK course
                    and this problem were assigned to you,
                    you would be able to submit an essay answer
                    that would be graded later by a human being.
                &lt;/P>!,
                PTX => '',
            );
            $out;
        };

        #### Suppress essay help link
        sub essay_help {};

        #### How many attempts until hint is available
        $showHint = -1;
        # May be a bug that WeBWorK requires -1 instead of 0
        # for immediate access to hints

        1;
        </pre>
        <p>Now <pretext/> will be able to communicate with this course to retrieve what is needed.</p>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="webwork-processing">
        <title>Processing</title>

        <subsection xml:id="extraction-and-merging">
            <title>Extraction and Merging</title>
            <p>A <pretext/> project that uses <webwork/> must first have its <webwork/> content extracted into an auxiliary XML file before anything else can be done. Use the <c>mbx</c> script to extract <pretext/> content from the <webwork/> server into a <em>folder</em>, which you might call <c>webwork-extraction/</c> as in this example:</p>

            <sidebyside>
                <console>
                    <prompt>$ </prompt>
                    <input>mbx -c webwork -s &lt;server&gt; -d webwork-extraction &lt;xml&gt;</input>
                </console>
            </sidebyside>

            <warning>
                <title>File Paths</title>
                <p>In the previous example and those that follow, you should specify paths as needed. For example, the <c>mbx</c> script is typically at <c>~/mathbook/script/mbx</c>. And the <c>-d</c> option is sepcifying a directory to place the auxiliary file, and if you literally use <c>-d webwork-extraction</c> instead of a full path, the expectation is that <c>webwork-extraction</c> is a folder in your current working folder.</p>
            </warning>

            <p><c>-c webwork</c> means you are processing the <webwork/> components.</p>

            <p><c>-s</c> specifies the <webwork/> server. The <webwork /> server needs to be version 2.14 or later, specified with its protocol and domain, like <c>https://webwork-ptx.aimath.org</c>. (If you do not have a server, you may use <c>https://webwork-ptx.aimath.org</c>.)</p>

            <p>If any of your hosting course, user for that course, password for the site, or password for the course user are not <c>anonymous</c>, then specify the server like
            <cd>-s "(https://webwork-ptx.aimath.org,courseID,userID,site_password,course_password)"</cd>
            The <c>site_password</c> is probably <q>anonymous</q>, but could be something different. Only server administrators can set this.</p>

            <p><c>-d</c> specifies a path to the folder where the auxiliary files will be stored. That folder is named <c>webwork-extraction</c> in the example. Any image files that the <webwork/> server generates will be stored inside this folder. An auxiliary XML <em>file</em> called <c>webwork-extraction.xml</c> will be created in this folder. (Note that you can name the folder whatever you like, but the auxiliary file that is created will always be named <c>webwork-extraction.xml</c>.)</p>

            <p>What is called <q><c>&lt;xml&gt;</c></q> in the example should be the root file for your <pretext/> project.</p>

            <p>The second phase of processing is to merge the extracted content with your original source tree. Use <c>xsltproc</c> with <c>pretext-merge.xsl</c> to do this as in this example:</p>

            <sidebyside>
                <console>
                    <prompt>$ </prompt>
                    <input>xsltproc --stringparam webwork.extraction webwork-extraction.xml pretext-merge.xsl &lt;xml&gt; > merge.ptx</input>
                </console>
            </sidebyside>

            <p>The string parameter <c>webwork.extraction</c> must identify the auxiliary XML file created in the previous step. Rather than literally typing <q><c>webwork-extraction.xml</c></q>, you likely need the full path to that file.</p>

            <p>What is called <q><c>&lt;xml&gt;</c></q> in the example should be the root file for your <pretext/> project.</p>

            <p>Store the merged XML tree in some file. The example stored it in <c>merge.ptx</c>. You may want to provide a path.</p>
        </subsection>

        <subsection>
            <title>HTML output</title>
            <p>When you execute <c>xsltproc</c><idx><c>xsltproc</c></idx> using <c>mathbook-html.xsl</c>, apply it to the merged file described above, not your original source. For example:</p>
            <sidebyside>
                <console>
                    <prompt>$ </prompt>
                    <input>xsltproc mathbook-html.xsl merge.ptx</input>
                </console>
            </sidebyside>
            <p>You may need to specify paths to <c>mathbook-html.xsl</c> and <c>merge.ptx</c>.</p>
            <p>There are several string parameters you may pass to <c>xsltproc</c>.</p>
            <sidebyside>
                <tabular valign="top">
                    <col />
                    <col width="60%" />
                    <row bottom="major">
                        <cell>stringparam</cell>
                        <cell>options</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row bottom="minor">
                        <cell><c>webwork.inline.static</c></cell>
                        <cell>
                            <p><c>'no'</c> (default) means inline exercises render as interactive.</p>
                            <p><c>'yes'</c> means inline exercises render as static.</p>
                            <p><c>'preview'</c> (planned) means inline exercises render as static until you click to activate them.</p>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row bottom="minor">
                        <cell><c>webwork.divisional.static</c></cell>
                        <cell>
                            <p><c>'no'</c> means divisional exercises render as interactive.</p>
                            <p><c>'yes'</c> (default) means divisional exercises render as static.</p>
                            <p><c>'preview'</c> (planned) means divisional exercises render as static until you click to activate them.</p>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row bottom="minor">
                        <cell><c>html.knowl.exercise.inline</c></cell>
                        <cell>
                            <p><c>'no'</c> means inline exercises appear on page load.</p>
                            <p><c>'yes'</c> (default) means inline exercises are hidden in knowls.</p>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row bottom="minor">
                        <cell><c>html.knowl.exercise.sectional</c></cell>
                        <cell>
                            <p><c>'no'</c> (default) means divisional exercises appear on page load.</p>
                            <p><c>'yes'</c> means divisional exercises are hidden in knowls.</p>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                </tabular>
            </sidebyside>

            <p>If your <webwork/> extraction included image files from the <webwork/> server and you are rendering the corresponding problems as static, then you need to copy the images files (from where your extracted auxiliary XML file was placed) over to where your HTML output assumes images files are located.</p>
        </subsection>

        <subsection xml:id="webwork-latex-output">
            <title><latex/> output</title>
            <p>When you execute <c>xsltproc</c><idx><c>xsltproc</c></idx> using <c>mathbook-latex.xsl</c>, apply it to the merged file described above, not your original source. For example:</p>
            <sidebyside>
                <console>
                    <prompt>$ </prompt>
                    <input>xsltproc mathbook-latex.xsl merge.ptx</input>
                </console>
            </sidebyside>
            <p>You may need to specify paths to <c>mathbook-latex.xsl</c> and <c>merge.ptx</c>.</p>

            <p>One string parameter you can pass to <c>xsltproc</c> is <c>latex.fillin.style</c>, which can take values <c>'underline'</c> (the default) or <c>'box'</c>.</p>

            <p>If your <webwork/> extraction included image files from the <webwork/> server , then you need to copy the images files (from where your extracted auxiliary XML file was placed) over to where your TeX output assumes images files are located.</p>
        </subsection>

        <subsection>
            <title>Creating Files for Uploading to <webwork/></title>

            <p>All of the <tag>webwork</tag> that you have written into your project can be <q>harvested</q> and put into their own <c>.pg</c> files by the <c>mbx</c> script. These files are created with a folder structure that follows the chunking scheme you specify. This process also creates set definition files (<c>.def</c>) for each chunk (say, for each section): one for inline exercises (checkpoints) and one for divisional exercises. For <tag>webwork</tag> problems that come from the <webwork/> server, the <c>.def</c> file will include them as well. This archiving process creates set header <c>.pg</c> files for each set definition.</p>

            <p>As with other <webwork/> processing, you must use the extraction and merge process first that is described in <xref ref="extraction-and-merging">Subsection</xref>. Then use <c>xsltproc</c> with <c>pretext-ww-problem-sets.xsl</c>. For example:</p>
            <sidebyside>
                <console>
                    <prompt>$ </prompt>
                    <input>xsltproc --stringparam chunk.level 2 pretext-ww-problem-sets.xsl merge.ptx</input>
                </console>
            </sidebyside>
            <p>You may need to specify paths to <c>pretext-ww-problem-sets.xsl</c> and <c>merge.ptx</c>.</p>

            <p>With a book, <c>--stringparam chunk.level 2</c> means that each problem set corresponds to a section from the book. Level 1: chapter. Level 3: subsection. With an article there are no chapters, and Level 1 corresponds to sections.</p>

            <p>This creates a folder named after your book title, which has a folder tree with all of the <c>.pg</c> and <c>.def</c> files laid out according to your chunk level. You can compress this folder and upload it into an active <webwork/> course where you may then assign the sets to your students (and modify, as you like).</p>
        </subsection>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Unachievable Conversions</title>

        <p>By authoring <webwork/> problems within <pretext/> you do not need to learn all the ins and outs of the <init>PGML</init> markup language and can concentrate on simply becoming proficient with <pretext/>.  However, there are a few <pretext/> constructions which are not achievable in a <webwork/> problem, simply because the two markup languages are different.  We list exceptions here, and also try to use source-checking tools to alert you to any differences.<ul>
            <li>
                <p>Certain aspects of specifying borders of a <pretext/> <tag>tabular</tag> are not realizable in a <init>PGML</init> table.  Specifically,<ul>
                    <li>Specifying column-specific top border attributes are not implemented.</li>
                    <li>Cell-specific bottom border attributes are not implemented.</li>
                    <li><c>medium</c> and <c>major</c> table rule-thichness attributes will be handled as if they were <c>minor</c>.</li>
                </ul></p>
            </li>
        </ul></p>
    </section>

</chapter>
