<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!--********************************************************************
Copyright 2015 Robert A. Beezer

This file is part of MathBook XML.

MathBook XML is free software: you can redistribute it and/or modify
it under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by
the Free Software Foundation, either version 2 or version 3 of the
License (at your option).

MathBook XML is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
GNU General Public License for more details.

You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
along with MathBook XML.  If not, see <http://www.gnu.org/licenses/>.
*********************************************************************-->
<!-- This file was originally part of the book     -->
<!-- (as copied on 2015/07/12)                     -->
<!--                                               -->
<!--   Abstract Algebra: Theory and Applications   -->
<!--                                               -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 2010-2014  Robert A. Beezer     -->

<exercises xml:id="groups-sage-exercises">
    <title>Sage Exercises</title>

    <introduction>
        <p>These exercises are about becoming comfortable working with groups in Sage.</p>
    </introduction>

    <exercise number="1">
        <statement>
            <p>Create the groups <c>CyclicPermutationGroup(8)</c> and <c>DihedralGroup(4)</c> and name these groups <c>C</c> and <c>D</c>, respectively.  We will understand these constructions better shortly, but for now just understand that both objects you create are actually groups.</p>
        </statement>
    </exercise>

    <exercise number="2">
        <statement>
            <p>Check that <c>C</c> and <c>D</c> have the same size by using the <c>.order()</c> method.  Determine which group is abelian, and which is not, by using the <c>.is_abelian()</c> method.</p>
        </statement>
    </exercise>

    <exercise number="3">
        <statement>
            <p>Use the <c>.cayley_table()</c> method to create the Cayley table for each group.</p>
        </statement>
    </exercise>

    <exercise number="4">
        <statement>
            <p>Write a nicely formatted discussion identifying differences between the two groups that are discernible in properties of their Cayley tables.  In other words, what is {\em different} about these two groups that you can <q>see</q> in the Cayley tables?  (In the Sage notebook, a Shift-click on a blue bar will bring up a mini-word-processor, and you can use use dollar signs to embed mathematics formatted using <tex/> syntax.)</p>
        </statement>
    </exercise>

    <exercise number="5">
        <statement>
            <p>For <c>C</c> locate the one subgroup of order <m>4</m>.  The group <c>D</c> has three subgroups of order <m>4</m>.  Select one of the three subgroups of <c>D</c> that has a different structure than the subgroup you obtained from <c>C</c>.</p>

            <p>The <c>.subgroups()</c> method will give you a list of all of the subgroups to help you get started.  A Cayley table will help you tell the difference between the two subgroups.  What properties of these tables did you use to determine the difference in the structure of the subgroups?</p>
        </statement>
    </exercise>

    <exercise number="6">
        <statement>
            <p>The <c>.subgroup(elt_list)</c> method of a group will create the smallest subgroup containing the specified elements of the group, when given the elements as a list <c>elt_list</c>.  Use this command to discover the shortest list of elements necessary to recreate the subgroups you found in the previous exercise.  The equality comparison, <c>==</c>, can be used to test if two subgroups are equal.</p>
        </statement>
    </exercise>

</exercises>
