<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!--   This file is part of the documentation of PreTeXt      -->
<!--                                                          -->
<!--        PreTeXt Developer's Guide                         -->
<!--                                                          -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 2019-2026                                  -->
<!-- Robert A. Beezer, David Farmer, Alex Jordan              -->
<!-- See the file COPYING for copying conditions.             -->

<chapter xml:id="css-source" label="css-source">
    <title>Styling with CSS and SCSS</title>
    <idx>CSS</idx>
    <idx>SCSS</idx>
    <idx><h>theme</h><h>development</h></idx>

    <introduction>
        <p>The <pretext/> conversion to <init>HTML</init> deliberately produces plain, semantic markup and leaves nearly all of the visual presentation to <init>CSS</init> (see <xref ref="online-style"/> for the publisher-facing view). This allows the same content to be styled in many different ways, and for new themes to be added without changing the conversion.  It also allows the styling to be shared across different output formats, such as web and print.</p>
        <p>To work well in this system, <init>HTML</init> generated by <init>XSL</init> or Javascript should avoid hard-coded inline <c>style</c>s attributes and instead use <c>class</c>es and <init>CSS</init> to control the styling.</p>
        <p>Every <init>HTML</init> book loads a single <c>theme.css</c> file, which is not written by hand but built from <init>SCSS</init> source by a small <c>node</c> script.  This chapter is a map of that source, so you can find your way around to adjust an existing theme or contribute a new one.  You do not need to be a web developer; a working knowledge of <init>CSS</init> and a willingness to read existing files is enough.</p>
    </introduction>

    <section xml:id="css-directory" label="css-directory">
        <title>The <c>css</c> Directory</title>

        <p>All styling source lives in the top-level <c>css</c> directory, whose <c>README.md</c> is the authoritative reference.  The folders are:<ul>
            <li><p><c>targets</c><mdash/>each <term>target</term> is a self-contained final product: one entry file that compiles to one <init>CSS</init> file.  The modern <init>HTML</init> themes are in <c>targets/html</c>, one folder per theme, named for a city (<c>default-modern</c>, <c>salem</c>, <c>denver</c>, <c>greeley</c>, <c>boulder</c>, <c>tacoma</c>).  Non-web targets (<c>epub</c>, <c>kindle</c>, <c>revealjs</c>, the print worksheet) live here too.  A file used by only one target belongs in that target's folder.</p></li>
            <li><p><c>components</c><mdash/>source shared across targets, grouped by what it styles: <c>chunks</c> (PreTeXt containers like exercises and knowls), <c>elements</c> (small pieces such as figures and lists), <c>page-parts</c> (table of contents, navigation bar, banner), <c>interactives</c> (Sage, Runestone, <webwork/>), and <c>helpers</c> (reusable mixins).  Editing a component affects every target that uses it.</p></li>
            <li><p><c>colors</c><mdash/>color <term>palettes</term> a theme can draw on, plus the master list of color variables (see <xref ref="css-colors"/>).</p></li>
            <li><p><c>fonts</c><mdash/>the mechanism a theme uses to select fonts.</p></li>
            <li><p><c>dist</c><mdash/>the built, ready-to-use <init>CSS</init> files (and source maps).  <em>Generated output<mdash/>never edit by hand</em> (see <xref ref="css-building"/>).</p></li>
            <li><p><c>legacy</c><mdash/>plain <init>CSS</init> for older themes that predate the <init>SCSS</init> system, kept for backward compatibility; new work does not go here.  <c>other</c> holds <init>CSS</init> that is not part of a book, such as the <pretext/> catalog.</p></li>
        </ul></p>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="css-building" label="css-building">
        <title>Building the CSS</title>

        <p>The distrubuted CSS files are build from <init>SCSS</init> (or <q>Sass</q>) source files. <init>SCSS</init> is a superset of <init>CSS</init> that adds variables, nesting, functions, and a module system (<c>@use</c>) for splitting styles across files. This source is built into ordinary <init>CSS</init> for use by the browser.
        </p>

        <p>Plain <init>CSS</init> is valid <init>SCSS</init>, so for the most part, adding styles to elements just involves writing normal <init>CSS</init>. The extra features of <init>SCSS</init> are only needed when you want to differentiate the <init>CSS</init> output for different themes or integrate with the color palettes. The <url href="https://sass-lang.com/guide/">Sass basics guide</url> is a good resource for learning about <init>SCSS</init> features.
        </p>

        <p>The build script is <c>script/cssbuilder</c>, run with <c>node</c>.  In normal use you never invoke it directly<mdash/>the <pretext/> script and the <init>CLI</init> build whatever theme a document needs.  The one-time setup is to install <c>node</c> and run <c>npm install</c> once in <c>script/cssbuilder</c> (the <init>CLI</init> does even this for you).  See <xref ref="node-and-npm"/> for <c>node</c> and <c>npm</c>. Once that is done, you can build all of the CSS targets from the <c>cssbuilder</c> directory with:</p>

        <console>
        <input prompt="script/cssbuilder$ ">npm run build</input>
        </console>

        <p>When working on the <init>CSS</init> for a feature, you will likely not want to build all the theme files and then have to rebuild your test book. Instead, you will likely want to update just the <init>CSS</init> directly in your book so you that you can examine styling updates without rebuilding the entire project or moving files around. The simplest way is to use the PreTeXt script's <c>-c theme</c> flag to rebuild only the theme (See <xref ref="pretext-script"/>) directly to your book.</p>

        <p>For finer control over which theme is built (to rapidly check different themes), or to have the CSS automatically rebuild when you change the source, you can run the build script directly with <c>node</c>. From the <c>script/cssbuilder</c> directory, do:</p>

        <console>
        <input prompt="script/cssbuilder$ ">npm run build -- -t theme-default-modern -o path_to_yourbook/_static/pretext/css -w</input>
        </console>

        <p>The <c>--</c> is required so the flags reach the script rather than <c>npm</c>.  Useful flags: <c>-t</c> (one target; <c>-l</c> lists them), <c>-o</c> (output directory), <c>-w</c> (watch and rebuild on changes), and <c>-c</c> (a <init>JSON</init> string of options and variables, the same ones a publisher sets, for trying colors and options).  Run <c>npm run build -- -h</c> for the full list; details are in <c>script/cssbuilder/README.md</c>.</p>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="css-theme-assembly" label="css-theme-assembly">
        <title>How a Theme Is Assembled</title>

        <p>Each PreTeXt work relies on a single <c>theme.css</c> file for all of its styling.  That file is built from a single <init>SCSS</init> entry file (for example <c>targets/html/default-modern/theme-default-modern.scss</c>) does three things: it declares the variables a publisher may override (each marked <c>!default</c>); it pulls in components and a color palette with <c>@use</c>; and it finishes by emitting the css variables defined by the imported files.</p>

        <p>The <c>css/README.md</c> describes ways themes are differentiated. In general, the files in a <c>target/</c> folder are only expected to be used by that target, so they can contain rules that are specific to that theme. Anything in the <c>components</c> folder is shared across targets, so it must work well across different themes and color palettes.</p>

        <p>Simple, local styles for a small component can likely be written without much extra work to integrate with various themes. The most likely complications are setting colors (<xref ref="css-colors"/>), fonts (<xref ref="css-fonts"/>), or items that need to be placed or sized relative to other elements on the page (<xref ref="css-sizing"/>).</p>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="css-colors" label="css-colors">
        <title>Colors and Palettes</title>

        <p>In general, styling rules should not contain hard-coded colors. A color that looks good in one theme (or set of colors for a theme) may not fit into another. And a color that works well in light mode may make something unreadable in dark mode.  Instead, colors should be expressed as <init>CSS</init> custom properties (variables) that a theme can be set to different values.</p>

        <p>For example, links in a PreTeXt document are set to <c>color: var(--link-text-color)</c> instead of something like <c>color: blue</c>. <c>--link-text-color</c> is set to a default color in <c>colors/_color-vars.scss</c>, But then each color palette overrides it as needed to fit the palette's overall color scheme.  In a theme that uses the dual palette, <c>--link-text-color</c> is defined as being the same as <c>var(--primary-color)</c>, which is set to match the color selected in the publisher file of the work.</p>

        <p>
            The easiest way to guarantee that new CSS will work reasonably well with every existing theme/mode is to use the existing color variables.
             <c>colors/_color-vars.scss</c> is the master list of every color, given semantic names (<c>--link-text-color</c>, not <c>--pretty-blue</c>). <term>palette</term> files (such as <c>_palette-dual.scss</c>) starts from that list, overrides the entries it cares about, and produces an <init>SCSS</init> map named <c>$colors</c>.  Each theme uses one of those palettes to set the color variables it will use.
        </p>

        <p>
            Say you are adding a feature that should look something like existing buttons. To match the existing style, first find the color variables used (<xref ref="css-making-changes"/>). Once you identify the relevant variables, such as <c>--button-background</c>, you can use them in your new CSS.
        </p>

        <note>
            <p>If you want to have something be <c>white</c> or <c>black</c> (in light mode), you should generally used <c>var(--content-background)</c> or <c>var(--body-text-color)</c> respectively. Those are good semantic choices for <q>the color of the background</q> and <q>the color of forground content</q> and will change appropriately in different palettes.</p>
        </note>

        <p>
            If you want to add finer control over the colors used by a new feature, add a new color variable to <c>colors/_color-vars.scss</c>, and use it in your CSS. To do so, you would write something like:
        </p>

        <program langauge="scss">
            "dropdown-background": var(--button-background),
        </program>

        <p>
            This ensures that the new variable has a default value (the button background color). Any palatte that targets multiple colors or dark mode will already have a value for <c>--button-background</c>, so your new variable will automatically work with those. Then, to customize the new variable for a particular palette like <c>_palette-dual.scss</c>, you would add an entry to the palette file, such as:
        </p>

        <code>
            "dropdown-background": var(--secondary-color),
        </code>

        <p>
            In a theme that uses the dual palette (like <c>default-modern</c>), the dropdown background will now be the secondary color, which is a different color than the button background. In a theme that uses a palette that does not customize <c>--dropdown-background</c>, the dropdown background will be the same as the button background.
        </p>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="css-fonts" label="css-fonts">
        <title>Font and Icons</title>

        <p><c>css/fonts</c> contains code to set up different font stacks for each theme. These font stacks are rendered into <init>CSS</init> variables:
            <ul>
                <li>
                    <c>--font-body</c><mdash/>the font used for the main text
                </li>
                <li>
                    <c>--font-headings</c><mdash/>the font used for headings
                </li>
                <li>
                    <c>--font-monospace</c><mdash/>the font used for code and other monospaced text
                </li>
            </ul>
        </p>
        <p>
            When writing new CSS, you can use these variables to ensure that your new feature uses the same fonts as the rest of the theme.
        </p>

        <p>Icons for various buttons and controls are provided for by the <url ref="https://fonts.google.com/icons">Google Material Symbols</url> font. To use an icon from this font, add the classes <c>icon material-symbols-outlined</c> to an element (typically a <tag>span</tag> or <tag>i</tag>) and set its content to the name of the icon you want. For example, to get a magnifying glass icon, you would write:</p>

        <program langage="html">
            &lt;span class="icon material-symbols-outlined" aria-hidden="true">search&lt;/span>
        </program>

        <p>The <c>aria-hidden="true"</c> is important for accessibility, as it tells screen readers to ignore the icon, which is typically decorative and does not convey information on its own. Equivalent information should be provided through other means, such as text labels or <init>ARIA</init> attributes.</p>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="css-sizing" label="css-sizing">
        <title>Sizing and Positioning Elements</title>

        <p>Elements that are placed or sized relative to the page or other top level structures of the page will likely need to leverage <init>SCSS</init> variables to work well across different themes. Many files have variables defined that look like this one from <c>css/components/page-parts/_body.scss</c>:</p>

        <code>$content-width: 600px !default;</code>

        <p>That variable can be overridden by a file that <c>@use</c>s it, but otherwise will have a default value of 600px. That variable can be used in style rules:</p>

        <program language="css">
            .ptx-page {
                max-width: $content-width;
                margin-left: auto;
                margin-right: auto;
            }
        </program>

        <p>When the <init>CSS</init> is built, the variable will be replaced by the appropriate value in each build target.</p>

        <p>A few of the most important sizing values are also rendered into <init>CSS</init> variables that can be referenced from anywhere. For example, <c>var(--base-content-width)</c> can be used to reference the standard width of the content area. Look for spots where <init>SCSS</init> variables are rendered into <init>CSS</init> variables like this:</p>

        <program language="css">
            :root {
                --base-content-width: #{$content-width};
                --content-padding: #{$content-side-padding};
            }
        </program>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="css-making-changes" label="css-making-changes">
        <title>Finding Styles and Making Changes</title>

        <p>If you are modifying existing styles or trying to identify how those will interact with your new content, begin by using your browser's developer tools to inspect the element you want to change. Identify the style rules that are currently applied and where those rules are located in the source<mdash/>the browser should tell you which <init>SCSS</init> file was responsible for each rule. You can also use the browser's developer tools to test changes to the style in real time before modifying the source.
        </p>

        <figure>
            <caption>Using the browser's developer tools to find and test styles</caption>
            <video label="browser-dev-tools-use" youtube="KVbjMNwLsjg"/>
        </figure>

        <p>Then using that information, find the relevant source file in the <c>css</c> directory. Make your changes, and then rebuild the theme (<xref ref="css-building"/>) to test. Make sure to test different screen sizes (desktop, tablet, mobile) using your browser's developer tools as well as in both light and dark modes.</p>

        <p>If the rules you have modified or added are in <q>shared</q> files like those in <c>components</c>, be aware that your change will affect every theme that uses that component, so you should check how it looks in other themes.</p>

        <p>You generally should have a commit for the CSS that is separate from the commit for the content changes that require it. For example, you might have one commit that updates the <init>XML</init> to produce new <init>HTML</init> and another commit that updates the corresponding <init>SCSS</init> styles for that content.</p>

        <p>The files in <c>css/dist</c> are checked into the repository so the common themes work without a build. However, your pull request should not <em>not</em> include updates to those files (stale builds tend to cause merge conflicts with other work that has been in progress). The individual merging the pull request is responsible for rebuilding them and committing the changes.</p>

        <p>Follow the usual conventions when submitting (<xref ref="code-style"/> and <xref ref="git-developer"/>), and raise larger ideas, such as a brand-new theme, on the <c>pretext-dev</c> discussion group first.</p>

    </section>

</chapter>
