<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!--   This file is part of the documentation of PreTeXt      -->
<!--                                                          -->
<!--      PreTeXt Author's Guide                              -->
<!--                                                          -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 2013-2017  Robert A. Beezer, David Farmer  -->
<!-- See the file COPYING for copying conditions.             -->

<chapter xml:id="production">
    <title>(*) Producing a Book</title>

    <introduction>
        <p>You have finished using <pretext /> to write a textbook, research monograph, laboratory manual, writer's handbook, or some other scholarly work, and you want to share it openly with students and other readers.  Good!  That's why we created <pretext />, and why we include this chapter.  There is more to do.</p>

        <p>This chapter will try to distill our personal experience, along with many conversations with other authors confronting these same decisions.  But recognize there is a lot of <em>advice</em> here, and a bit of an attitude, simply for your consideration.  The decisions are yours.</p>

        <aside>
            <title>Open Source</title>
            <p><pretext /> is open source <em>software</em>, but that places no restrictions on how you use output that <pretext /> creates (see <xref ref="principle-open-software" />).  You are welcome to sell your copyright to a commercial publisher or university press.  But just once, here and now, we will encourage you to consider an open license (see <xref ref="open-licenses" />) as a way of paying it forward.</p>
        </aside>
    </introduction>

    <section>
        <title>(*) Front Matter</title>
        <p>TODO</p>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="landing-page">
        <title>Landing Page</title>
        <idx><h>landing page</h></idx>
        <idx><h>project website</h></idx>
        <idx><h>website</h><h>for a project</h></idx>
        <idx><h>GitHub Pages</h></idx>

        <p>A single book can yield many different outputs<mdash/>an online <init>HTML</init> version, a <init>PDF</init> for the screen or for print (<xref ref="print-on-demand"/>), perhaps an <init>EPUB</init> or a packet of worksheets.  We think every project deserves one thing more: a <term>landing page</term>, the home page of a small website devoted to the project as a whole.  It is the front door<mdash/>the one stable, memorable <init>URL</init> you advertise on a syllabus, cite in a talk, or hand to a colleague<mdash/>and from it a reader can reach whichever version they prefer.</p>

        <p>A landing page is <em>not</em> the <init>HTML</init> index page (<xref ref="index-page"/>).  That index page is the <c>index.html</c> file <pretext/> builds <em>inside</em> your <init>HTML</init> output so that a directory <init>URL</init> resolves to a sensible first page of the book; it belongs to a single output.  A landing page sits <em>above</em> all of your outputs and introduces the project itself: a short description, a cover image, links to the current online version and to a downloadable <init>PDF</init>, perhaps errata or news, and a way to contact you or to adopt the book.</p>

        <p>Because the landing page is what endures as versions come and go, and as hosting arrangements change, it is worth situating at a domain name you own and control (<xref ref="web-hosting"/>), so the project can move without breaking the links others have already made to it.</p>

        <p>The PreTeXt-CLI can assemble such a site for you.  When you deploy more than one target (<xref ref="processing-CLI-deploy"/>), you place your landing page in a <c>site</c> folder at the root of your project, and <c>pretext deploy</c> stages that page together with each target's output as a single website.  For hosting, <url href="https://pages.github.com/" visual="pages.github.com/">GitHub Pages</url> is a natural, free home (<xref ref="web-hosting"/>).  This holds even when the book itself is hosted elsewhere: a Runestone book, for instance, already lives in a GitHub repository, so GitHub Pages is immediately available to carry the project's landing page.</p>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>(*) Source</title>
        <p>TODO</p>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>(*) Marketing</title>

        <introduction>
            <p>Didn't think about that one?  Write it, and they will come?  Not necessarily.  I have seen nice projects where authors make little extra effort to get the word out, and it shows.  With the Internet, effective promotion can be accomplished without much effort or expense.  And very soon your project can rise very high in search engine rankings.</p>
        </introduction>

        <subsection>
            <title>(*) Social Media</title>
        <p>TODO</p>
        </subsection>

        <subsection>
            <title>(*) Reference Sites</title>
        <p>TODO</p>
        </subsection>

        <subsection>
            <title>(*) Analytics</title>
        <p>TODO</p>
        </subsection>

        <subsection>
            <title>(*) Discussion Groups</title>
        <p>TODO</p>
        </subsection>
    </section>

</chapter>
