<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!--   This file is part of the documentation of PreTeXt      -->
<!--                                                          -->
<!--      PreTeXt Publisher's Guide                           -->
<!--                                                          -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 2013-2017  Robert A. Beezer, David Farmer  -->
<!-- See the file COPYING for copying conditions.             -->

<!-- NB: This chapter is organized by the hierarchy -->
<!-- of the publisher file and then alphabetically  -->
<!-- at each level of the tree                      -->

<chapter xml:id="publisher-file-reference">
    <title>Publisher File Reference</title>

    <introduction>
        <p>This chapter is reference material for the <term>publisher file</term>, whose employment is described in <xref ref="publisher-file"/>.</p>
    </introduction>

    <section xml:id="publisher-file-latex">
        <title>PDF (<latex/>) Options</title>
        <idx>PDF publisher options</idx>
        <idx>LaTeX publisher options</idx>
        <idx><h>publisher options</h><h>PDF</h></idx>
        <idx><h>publisher options</h><h>LaTeX</h></idx>

        <introduction>
            <p>These options affect the conversion to <latex/>, which can in turn be converted into <init>PDF</init>.
            See <xref ref="pdf-print"/> for a more general overview of this conversion with more details.  This includes some existing options that will eventually migrate to the publisher file.</p>
        </introduction>

        <subsection xml:id="latex-print-options">
            <title><latex/> Print Option</title>
            <idx><h>print option</h><h>LaTeX, PDF</h></idx>
            <idx><h>electronic option</h><h>LaTeX, PDF</h></idx>
            <idx><h>LaTeX</h><h>print option</h></idx>
            <idx><h>LaTeX</h><h>electronic option</h></idx>
            <idx><h>PDF</h><h>print option</h></idx>
            <idx><h>PDF</h><h>electronic option</h></idx>

            <p>The conversion to <latex/> can produce a <init>PDF</init> optimized for print, or optimized for use electronically on a screen.  The<cd>
                <cline>/publication/latex/@print</cline>
            </cd>attribute can have the value <c>yes</c> to produce a print version, or the value <c>no</c> to produce an electronic version.  The default is an electronic version.  See the introduction to <xref ref="pdf-print"/> for more detail.</p>
        </subsection>

    <section xml:id="publisher-file-online">
        <title>Online (HTML) Options</title>
        <idx>HTML publisher options</idx>
        <idx><h>publisher options</h><h>HTML</h></idx>

        <introduction>
            <p>These options affect the base conversion to web pages (online, <init>HTML</init>).  Many, but not all, will affect subsequent conversions based on <init>HTML</init>, such as a conversion to <itnit>EPUB</itnit> or Jupyter notebooks.  See <xref ref="online-html"/>  for a more general overview of this conversion, including options that will eventually migrate here.</p>
        </introduction>

        <subsection xml:id="online-analytics-options">
            <title>HTML Analytics</title>
            <idx>analytics</idx>

            <p>The<cd>
                <cline>/publication/html/analytics</cline>
            </cd>element can have the following attributes:<ul>
                <li><attr>google-gst</attr>: a Google <term>global site tag</term>, and ID you get from Google.  <em>Do not copy the identification numbers from another project<mdash/>be sure to obtain your own for your project.</em></li>
                <li><attr>statcounter-project</attr>, <attr>statcounter-security</attr>: ID numbers you get from StatCounter.  <em>Do not copy the identification numbers from another project<mdash/>be sure to obtain your own for your project.</em></li>
            </ul>Setting these attributes to non-empty strings is the signal to add the relevant code to each of the pages of your HTML output.  See <xref ref="online-analytics"/> for more.</p>
        </subsection>

        <subsection xml:id="online-calculator">
            <title>HTML Embedded Calculator</title>
            <idx><h>calculator</h><h>embedded in <init>HTML</init></h></idx>

            <p>The<cd>
                <cline>/publication/html/calculator</cline>
            </cd>element has the following attributes:<ul>
                <li>
                    <p><attr>model</attr>: used to control which calculator is available on every page.  Possible values are:<ul>
                        <li><c>geogebra-classic</c></li>
                        <li><c>geogebra-graphing</c></li>
                        <li><c>geogebra-geometry</c></li>
                        <li><c>geogebra-3d</c></li>
                        <li><c>none</c></li>
                    </ul></p>
                </li>
            </ul>  See <xref ref="online-embedded-calculator" text="title"/> in <xref ref="html-publisher-options"/> for more.</p>
        </subsection>

        <subsection xml:id="online-index-page">
            <title>HTML Index Page</title>
            <idx><h>index page</h><h>HTML</h></idx>
            <idx><h>HTML</h><h>index page</h></idx>

            <p>The<cd>
                <cline>/publication/html/index-page</cline>
            </cd>element can have the following attribute:<ul>
                <li><attr>ref</attr>: the <attr>xml:id</attr> of a division which will be a complete page at whatever level the document is chunked (broken into smaller pages).</li>
            </ul>An <c>index.html</c> page will be created which redirects immediately to this page.  Many webservers will serve this page when a <init>URL</init> stops with the enclosing directory.  So the Table of Contents (<tag>book</tag>, <tag>article</tag>) or the <tag>frontmatter</tag> are common choices.  See <xref ref="index-page" text="title"/> in <xref ref="html-publisher-options"/> for more.</p>
        </subsection>

        <subsection xml:id="online-platform-options">
            <title>HTML Platforms</title>
            <idx><h>platform</h><h>HTML</h></idx>
            <idx>online platforms</idx>

            <p>The<cd>
                <cline>/publication/html</cline>
            </cd>element can have an attribute <attr>platform</attr> with values:<ul>
                <li><c>web</c>: the default, meant for self-hosting with no server configuration, features, or assumptions</li>
                <li><c>runestone</c>: output meant for hosting on a Runestone server (<xref ref="runestone"/>)</li>
            </ul>Here <term>platform</term> refers to the server where the <init>HTML</init> output will eventually be hosted.  The effect is to create minor variations in the output to take advantage of extra features of the indicated platform.</p>
        </subsection>

        <subsection xml:id="online-style-options">
            <title>HTML Style</title>
            <idx><h>style</h><h>HTML</h></idx>

            <p>The<cd>
                <cline>/publication/html/css</cline>
            </cd>element can have the following attributes:<ul>
                <li><attr>colors</attr>: used to construct filename for CSS controlling colors.</li>
                <li><attr>knowls</attr>: used to construct filename for CSS controlling knowls.</li>
                <li><attr>toc</attr>: used to construct filename for CSS controlling the Table of Contents.</li>
                <li><attr>banner</attr>: used to construct filename for CSS controlling the banner (masthead).</li>
            </ul>In each case the default file is replaced and instead a new filename is formed from the attributes value.  For example, the specification<cd>
                <cline>&lt;css colors='bright_red'/&gt;</cline>
            </cd>will cause a CSS file named <c>colors_bright_red.css</c> to replace <c>colors_default.css</c>.  The server in use can be configured separately.  See <xref ref="online-style"/> for more.</p>

            <p>2019-12-08: at this time we recommend experimenting with only one file at a time.</p>
        </subsection>

        <subsection xml:id="online-search-options">
            <title>HTML Search</title>
            <idx>search</idx>

            <p>The<cd>
                <cline>/publication/html/search</cline>
            </cd>element can have the following attribute:<ul>
                <li><attr>google-cx</attr>: a Google <term>cx number</term>, gained from configuring search for a site.</li>
            </ul>Setting this attributes to a non-empty string is the signal to add the relevant code for a search box in the masthead.  See <xref ref="online-search"/> for more.</p>
        </subsection>

        <subsection xml:id="embedded-video-privacy-options">
            <title>HTML Video Embedding</title>
            <idx><h>video</h><h>embedding</h></idx>
            <idx><h>privacy</h><h>video</h></idx>

            <p>The<cd>
                <cline>/publication/html/video</cline>
            </cd>element can have the following attribute:<ul>
                <li><attr>privacy</attr>: allowed values are <c>yes</c> or <c>no</c>.</li>
            </ul>Setting this to yes (the default) prevents certain tracking cookies from being used. Currently only supported for videos from YouTube. See <xref ref="video-embedding" text="title"/> in <xref ref="html-publisher-options"/> for more.</p>
        </subsection>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="publisher-file-revealjs">
        <title>Reveal.js Slideshow Options</title>
        <idx>reveal.js slideshow publisher options</idx>
        <idx><h>publisher options</h><h>reveal.js slideshow</h></idx>

        <introduction>
            <p>See <xref ref="publisher-revealjs"/> for a more general overview of this conversion.</p>
        </introduction>

        <subsection xml:id="revealjs-appearance-options">
            <title>Reveal.js Appearance</title>
            <idx><h>publisher options</h><h>reveal.js appearance</h></idx>

            <p>The<cd>
                <cline>/publication/revealjs/appearance</cline>
            </cd>element can have the following attribute:<ul>
                <li><attr>theme</attr>: the base name of a file that is a reveal.js theme.  For example if the desired theme/CSS file is <c>css/theme/solarized.css</c>, then set the value of this attribute to <c>solarized</c>.</li>
            </ul></p>
        </subsection>

        <subsection xml:id="revealjs-control-options">
            <title>Reveal.js Controls</title>
            <idx><h>publisher options</h><h>reveal.js controls</h></idx>

            <p>The<cd>
                <cline>/publication/revealjs/controls</cline>
            </cd>element can have the following attributes:<ul>
                <li><attr>backarrow</attr>: for the visibility of a <q>back</q> arrow.  Values are <c>faded</c>, <c>hidden</c>, or <c>visible</c>.  The default is <c>faded</c>.</li>
                <li><attr>display</attr>: for the overall visibility of controls.  Values are <c>yes</c> or <c>no</c>.  The default is <c>yes</c>.</li>
                <li><attr>layout</attr>: for the location of the controls.  Values are <c>edges</c> or <c>bottom-right</c>.  The default is <c>bottom-right</c>.</li>
                <li><attr>tutorial</attr>: for animation of suggested navigation arrows.  Values are <c>yes</c> or <c>no</c>.  The default is <c>yes</c>.</li>
            </ul></p>
        </subsection>

        <subsection xml:id="revealjs-navigation-options">
            <title>Reveal.js Navigation</title>
            <idx><h>publisher options</h><h>reveal.js navigation</h></idx>

            <p>The<cd>
                <cline>/publication/revealjs/navigation</cline>
            </cd>element can have the following attribute:<ul>
                <li><attr>mode</attr>: for the arrangement of the navigation through slides.  Values are <c>default</c>, <c>linear</c>, or <c>grid</c>.  The default is <c>default</c>.  The value <c>default</c> refers to the default mode of Reveal.js and is synonomous with <c>grid</c>.  In other words, the choice of <c>default</c> or <c>grid</c> results in identical behavior.</li>
            </ul>See <xref ref="publisher-revealjs"/> for more explanation of the two different navigation modes.</p>
        </subsection>

        <subsection xml:id="revealjs-resources-options">
            <title>Reveal.js Resources</title>
            <idx><h>publisher options</h><h>reveal.js resources</h></idx>

            <p>You may wish to host the reveal.js CSS and javascript files locally or obtain them online.  Be sure to read in  <xref ref="publisher-revealjs"/> about the necessity of providing the complete MathJax library <xref ref="publisher-revealjs"/> if your document has mathematics and you opt for local resources.</p>

            <p>The<cd>
                <cline>/publication/revealjs/resources</cline>
            </cd>element can have the following attributes:<ul>
                <li><attr>host</attr>: The values <c>local</c> and <c>cdn</c> will retrieve various Javascript and CSS files (such as the theme) relative to the slideshow <init>HTML</init> file or from an online Content Delivery Network (respectively).  PreTeXt will maintain a link to a current, updated, <init>CDN</init> version and this will change without notice.  This attribute may be given a <init>URL</init> or a local path, though this has not been tested, so should be considered experimental.</li>
                <li><attr>minified</attr>: These files may be compressed into a <q>min-ified</q> form for faster downloading.  Typically the <init>CDN</init> files will be available in this form, while the local version will not.  <pretext/> will make a sensible choice based on <attr>host</attr>, so you should only need to use this attribute to override that choice.  Values are <c>yes</c> and <c>no</c>.</li>
            </ul></p>
        </subsection>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="publisher-file-source">
        <title>Source Options</title>
        <idx>source publisher options</idx>
        <idx><h>publisher options</h><h>source</h></idx>

        <introduction>
            <p>Some source material is optional, and may be included based on the publisher and the audience.</p>
        </introduction>

        <p>The<cd>
            <cline>/publication/source</cline>
        </cd>element can have the following attributes:<ul>
            <li><attr>private-solutions</attr>: A filename for a structured file of <tag>hint</tag>, <tag>answer</tag>, <tag>solution</tag> that will see limited distribution (for example, instructors only).  A relative path for the filename is relative to the main source file.  Try an absolute path if there are any problems.  See <xref ref="private-solutions-file"/> for details about the use of a private solutions file.</li>
            <li><attr>webwork-problems</attr>: A filename for a structured file of multiple representatiions of <webwork/> problems.  See <xref ref="representations-publisher"/> for details about the use of a <webwork/> representations file.</li>
        </ul></p>

    </section>

</chapter>
