<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!--   This file is part of the documentation of PreTeXt      -->
<!--                                                          -->
<!--      PreTeXt Publisher's Guide                           -->
<!--                                                          -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 2013-2017  Robert A. Beezer, David Farmer  -->
<!-- See the file COPYING for copying conditions.             -->

<chapter xml:id="publisher-file-reference">
    <title>Publisher File Reference</title>

    <introduction>
        <p>This chapter is reference material for the <term>publisher file</term>, whose employment is described in <xref ref="publisher-file"/>.</p>
    </introduction>

    <section xml:id="analytics-options">
        <title>HTML Analytics</title>
        <idx>analytics</idx>

        <p>The<cd>
            <cline>/publisher/html/analytics</cline>
        </cd>element can have the following attributes:<ul>
            <li><attr>goggle-gst</attr>: a Google <term>global site tag</term>, and ID you get from Google.</li>
            <li><attr>statcounter-project</attr>, <attr>statcounter-security</attr>: ID numbers you get from StatCounter.</li>
        </ul>Setting these attributes to non-empty strings is the signal to add the relevant code to each of the pages of your HTML output.  See <xref ref="online-analytics"/> for more.</p>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="online-style-options">
        <title>HTML Style</title>
        <idx><h>style</h><h>HTML</h></idx>

        <p>The<cd>
            <cline>/publisher/html/css</cline>
        </cd>element can have the following attributes:<ul>
            <li><attr>colors</attr>: used to construct filename for CSS controlling colors.</li>
            <li><attr>knowls</attr>: used to construct filename for CSS controlling knowls.</li>
            <li><attr>toc</attr>: used to construct filename for CSS controlling the Table of Contents.</li>
            <li><attr>banner</attr>: used to construct filename for CSS controlling the banner (masthead).</li>
        </ul>In each case the default file is replaced and instead a new filename is formed from the attributes value.  For example, the specification<cd>
            <cline>&lt;css colors='bright_red'/&gt;</cline>
        </cd>will cause a CSS file named <c>colors_bright_red.css</c> to replace <c>colors_default.css</c>.  The server in use can be configured separately.  See <xref ref="online-style"/> for more.</p>

        <p>2019-12-08: at this time we recommend experimenting with only one file at a time.</p>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="search-options">
        <title>HTML search</title>
        <idx>search</idx>

        <p>The<cd>
            <cline>/publisher/html/search</cline>
        </cd>element can have the following attribute:<ul>
            <li><attr>goggle-cx</attr>: a Google <term>cx number</term>, gained from configuring search for a site.</li>
        </ul>Setting this attributes to a non-empty string is the signal to add the relevant code for a search box in the masthead.  See <xref ref="online-search"/> for more.</p>
    </section>

</chapter>
