<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!--   This file is part of the documentation of PreTeXt      -->
<!--                                                          -->
<!--      PreTeXt Publisher's Guide                           -->
<!--                                                          -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 2013-2017  Robert A. Beezer, David Farmer  -->
<!-- See the file COPYING for copying conditions.             -->

<chapter xml:id="runestone">
    <title>Conversion to Runestone</title>

        <!-- indentation is off, for a clean commit as re-arranged -->

        <p><url href="https://runestone.academy" visual="runestone.academy">Runestone Interactive</url> is a textbook authoring and hosting system orginally designed for textbooks about computer science.  It is similar in design and goals to <pretext/>, but is also complementary in important ways.  In particular, Runestone provides textbook hosting and excels at providing very interactive versions where student work in the textbook can be graded (automatically or manually), scores recorded, and that information can be viewed by an instructor.</p>

        <p>The usual <pretext/> <init>HTML</init> output (<xref ref="online-html"/>) only needs minor modifications to run profitably on a Runestone server.  You accomplish this via a publisher option (<xref ref="publication-file"/>).  The absolute simplest publication file to accomplish this is<cd>
            <cline>&lt;publication&gt;</cline>
            <cline>  &lt;html&gt;</cline>
            <cline>    &lt;platform host="runestone"/&gt;</cline>
            <cline>  &lt;/html&gt;</cline>
            <cline>&lt;/publication&gt;</cline>
        </cd>(See <xref ref="online-platform-options"/>.)  Then perform the usual conversion to online <init>HTML</init>, as described in <xref ref="online-html"/> but also include the publication file via a string parameter.  The output should appear like a usual <pretext/> document, but will now include a new menu on each page.  This has options which allow a reader or instructor to interact with the server when hosted.</p>

        <p>Runestone textbooks are designed around interactive activities and active reading.  We are in the process of exposing these capabilities via <pretext/> markup, as of 2022-01-21.  So expect this list to expand, and feel free to influence priorities for new features.  Some of this is subject to change as we gain experience.<ul>
            <li>Every feature of <pretext/> <init>HTML</init> output should function identically on a Runestone server.</li>
            <li>Any <tag>exercise</tag> authored in a <pretext/> <tag>reading-questions</tag> division will automatically be rendered as a Runestone short answer question.  A student can use <latex/> notation in formulating their answer, and Runestone will provide the instructor an efficient interface for reviewing student responses, provide feedback, and assign scores.</li>
            <li>A <pretext/> <tag>program</tag> element with the attribute <attr>interactive</attr> set to <c>yes</c> will be realized as a Runestone ActiveCode element.  The <attr>language</attr> must also be set.  Supported values for the language are: <c>python</c>, <c>python2</c>, <c>python3</c>, <c>c</c>, <c>cpp (C++)</c>, <c>javascript</c>, <c>java</c>, <c>sql</c>, and <c>html</c>.</li>
            <li>More <pretext/> markup for exercises realized in a Runestone book is coming and will go here.</li>
            <li>All of the exercises adapted automatically for Runestone (i.e. reading questions, programming exercises) can be worked by a student at the location in the book where they were authored, or a student may use the interface provided by the server to locate assigned problems, at a page disjoint from the text itself.</li>
            <li>Students and instructors are provided extensive reports on progress.</li>
            <li>Instructors may download a spreadsheet of scores at any time.</li>
        </ul></p>

        <p>We will not attempt to duplicate Runestone's documentation here.  Visit the <url href="https://runestone.academy" visual="runestone.academy">Runestone Academy</url> site to learn more.</p>
</chapter>
