<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<chapter xml:id="publisher-slides">
    <title>Conversion to Slides</title>
    <idx>slides</idx>
    <introduction>
        <p>
            As discussed in <xref ref="overview-slides"/> and <xref ref="topic-slides"/>,
            support is available for authoring slideshows in <pretext/>. Currently, slideshows
            must be authored explicitly, but we hope to eventually support annotating
            books and articles to export appropriate content as slides.
        </p>
    </introduction>
    <section xml:id="publisher-revealjs">
        <title>Reveal.js</title>
        <p>
            Run this to produce a Reveal.js slideshow:<cd>
                <cline>xsltproc --xinclude -o path/to/output/slides.html</cline>
                <cline>  --stringparam publisher path/to/source/publication.xml</cline>
                <cline>  path/to/pretext/xsl/pretext-revealjs.xsl path/to/source/slides.xml</cline>
            </cd>
        </p>
        <p>
            Reveal.js supports themes that affect the overall appearance of a slideshow.
            So in <pretext/> you can specify the name of theme in a publisher file.
            See <xref ref="revealjs-appearance-options"/> for details.
        </p>
        <p>
            You might assume that your slideshow will be presented with the internet available,
            perhaps in a classroom, and will be updated for use the next semester.
            Or maybe you are presenting at a conference where you do not want to trust an unfamiliar internet connection,
            and you will later host an archival version of your presentation on your website and you want it to <q>just work</q> ten years from now.
            So you can configure your slideshow to obtain resources from a Content Delivery Network (<init>CDN</init>) online,
            or you may arrange to copy the necessary files from reveal.js and store them locally (your hard disk, your website).
            See <xref ref="revealjs-resources-options"/> for details on specifying these options, and see below for directions on how to organize the Reveal.js support files.
        </p>
        <p>
            Reveal.js will render <latex/> syntax with MathJax,
            entirely similar to how MathJax is used in the <pretext/> conversion to <init>HTML</init>.
            This is accomplished with the Reveal.js <c>math</c> plugin, which is loaded automatically as part of your output.  When you specify that resources come from a CDN, then this plugin will also get MathJax from a CDN.
            When you specify that resources are available locally (your hard disk, your website),
            then the plugin itself will be obtained locally, but MathJax will still be obtained from a CDN.
            So a local version may only be practical if you are careful not to include <em>any</em> mathematics in your document.
            (Reveal.js <em>can</em> be configured to use a locally installed copy of MathJax, but we have not provided any support for this scenario.)
        </p>
        <p>
            We are not enthusiastic about <init>PDF</init> as an electronic format.
            But it might be a good choice as an archival format.
            So exporting your slideshow to a <init>PDF</init> could be a good choice for a long-term archive.
            On 2020-08-01 Andrew Rechnitzer suggests the <url href="https://github.com/astefanutti/decktape" visual="github.com/astefanutti/decktape"><c>decktape</c></url> node (Javascript) program.
            The <c>reveal</c> plugin works well once you settle on a resolution (the <c>-s</c> option).
            The <c>generic</c> plugin, along with the default key action (<c>ArrowRight</c>) can capture the behavior of slides built using the <attr>pause</attr> attribute.
            A local web server can also be employed to serve up the slides, see <xref ref="processing-testing-html"/>.
        </p>
        <paragraphs>
            <title>Navigation Mode</title>
            <p>
                Reveal.js has various options of the visibility of arrows a presenter can click on in order to move through a presentation.
                The visibility of these can be controlled via options in the publisher file.  See <xref ref="revealjs-control-options"/>.
            </p>
            <p>
                Reveal.js imagines slides laid out on a 2-D grid.  Each <pretext/> section gives rise to a title slide and these are organized left-to-right.  <em>Below</em> each of these slides, arranged vertically, are the slides comprising the section.  We use the attribute value <c>grid</c> to refer to this arrangement.
            </p>
            <p>
                If public speaking makes you nervous and going left-to-right and top-to-bottom
                nearly simultaneously means you get lost and even less confident (we've seen it),
                we have an option for you.
                The attribute value <c>linear</c> arranges <em>all</em> your slides from left-to-right.
                Aah, that's better.
                See <xref ref="revealjs-navigation-options"/> for details on setting the navigation mode for your slideshow.
            </p>
        </paragraphs>
        <paragraphs>
            <title>Local Resources</title>
            <p>
                To set up a Reveal.js slideshow to run locally, you need to have certain files available locally.  We describe here the exact mechanics of doing this.
            </p>
            <p>
                Suppose you have done the <pretext/> conversion, and have created a single <c>slides.html</c> file, which you have placed in a directory named <c>talk</c>.  Now download or clone the git repository for Reveal.js (<url href="https://github.com/hakimel/reveal.js/" visual="github.com/hakimel/reveal.js"/>).  This has a <c>dist</c> directory with four files, such as <c>reveal.css</c>, and also directory of themes, named <c>theme</c>.  Copy these files and the directory to <c>talk</c>.  Another directory in the repository is named <c>plugin</c>.  Copy this directory to <c>talk</c> as well.
            </p>
            <p>
                This process will duplicate more files than you need.  Suppose your talk is produced to use the <c>solarized</c> theme (<xref ref="revealjs-appearance-options"/>), and includes some math.  Then as an example of how the copying should go, and as an example of the bare minimum necessary, your <c>talk</c> directory should be organized as follows.
            </p>

            <pre>
            talk
                slides.html
                reset.css
                reveal.css
                reveal.js
                theme
                    solarized.css
                plugin
                    math
                        math.js
                        plugin.js
            </pre>
        </paragraphs>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="publisher-beamer">
        <title>Beamer <latex/></title>
        <p>
            Run this to produce a Beamer <latex/> slideshow:<cd>
                <cline>xsltproc --xinclude -o path/to/output/slides.tex</cline>
                <cline>  path/to/pretext/xsl/pretext-beamer.xsl path/to/source/slides.xml</cline>
            </cd>
        </p>
        <p>
            Of course, you should then run e.g. <c>pdflatex slides.tex</c> to produce a PDF.
        </p>
    </section>
</chapter>
