<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!--   This file is part of the documentation of PreTeXt      -->
<!--                                                          -->
<!--      PreTeXt Author's Guide                              -->
<!--                                                          -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 2013-2016  Robert A. Beezer                -->
<!-- See the file COPYING for copying conditions.             -->

<chapter xml:id="webwork-publisher">
  <title><webwork/> Exercises</title>
  <idx>
    <h><webwork/></h>
    <h><webwork/> exercises</h>
  </idx>
  <author>Alex Jordan</author>

  <introduction>
    <p>
      With a <webwork/> server
      (version 2.16 or higher, or <url href="https://webwork-ptx.aimath.org" visual="webwork-ptx.aimath.org"/>)
      and a little setup work, you can embed <webwork/> exercises in your <pretext/> project.
      HTML output can have interactive problem cells or print problems in <q>static</q> form.
      PDF output will print static versions.
      And all such exercises can be archived into a file tree to be uploaded onto a <webwork/> server
      for use in the <q>traditional</q> way.
    </p>
    <p>
      Part of the process can optionally be sped up by using a local copy of the <c>pg</c>
      repository.
    </p>
    <p>
      See <xref ref="webwork-author"/> for how to include or create <webwork/> problems in your source.
    </p>
  </introduction>

  <section xml:id="webwork-local-pg-static-processing">
    <title>Using a Local Copy of PG</title>
    <p>
      <webwork/> problems can be processed using a local copy of the <c>pg</c> repository. This can
      siginificanlty speed up processing time, compared with the other options that use a network
      connection.
    </p>
    <p>
      To use this processing method, clone the <c>pg</c> repository. The code below places it in a
      default location, but you could place it somewhere else.
      <cd>
        <cline>cd /opt</cline>
        <cline>mkdir webwork</cline>
        <cline>cd webwork</cline>
        <cline>git clone https://github.com/openwebwork/pg</cline>
      </cd>
      Note that you should end up with a verion of <c>pg</c> that is 2.19 or later. To check, examine
      the <c>VERSION</c> file in the root of the repository.
    </p>
    <p>
      Set the <c>PG_ROOT</c> environment variable to be the path to your copy of <c>pg</c>. If it is
      at the default location, you could run:
      <cd>export PG_ROOT=/opt/webwork/pg</cd>
      This will only define <c>$PG_ROOT</c> for your current terminal session, so you might also do
      whatever is appropriate on your system to set <c>PG_ROOT</c> each time a terminal session
      begins.
    </p>
    <p>
      In <c>pg/conf/</c>, make a copy of <c>pg_config.dist.yml</c> called <c>pg_config.yml</c>. In
      general you should read through all the settings and set them appropriately. At a minimum, set
      <c>directories: root:</c> to the absolute path to your clone of <c>pg</c>. You may need to set
      paths in <c>externalPrograms:</c> as well. And maybe more...
    </p>
    <p>
      For <pretext/> in general you should already have ImageMagick installed. Somewhere in your
      file system is an XML file that ImageMagick uses to control permissions. The file is named
      <c>policy.xml</c> and might be located in a place like <c>/etc/imagemagick/policy.xml</c>
      or <c>/etc/ImageMagick-6/policy.xml</c>. (If your version of ImageMagick is not 6, it's
      possible none of this is necessary. But also it should be harmless to continue.) In this file,
      within the <tag>policymap</tag> element, add the element:
      <cd>&lt;policy domain="coder" rights="read" pattern="PDF" /></cd>
      Depending on your file, you may need to <em>replace</em> a similar line that is assigning
      <c>rights="none"</c>. Make sure that this is not within a commented out portion of the file.
    </p>
    <p>
      You need to have a recent enough perl version. Version 5.32 is known to work, and versions as
      early as 5.26 may work, but have not been thoroughly tested.
    </p>
    <p>
      PG also uses perl packages that you may not yet have and need to install. These may be
      available from Linux package distributions, and the details differ from one flavor of Linux to
      the next. Alternatively there is a utility called <c>cpanm</c> (cpanminus) that is supposed
      to let you manage perl module installation across Linux flavors. One important difference is
      that <c>cpanm</c> only mangages perl modules. And sometimes a perl module is actually an
      interface between perl and some other system utility. <c>cpanm</c> will not actually install
      that system utility that it depends on and will just quit. Whereas Linux package distributions
      will have a more sophisticated dependency understanding, and try to install non-perl tools
      when needed. So you want to try to use Linux package distributions where you can. Or else use
      <c>cpanm</c> and perhaps be prepared to read the log if it fails and attempt to install some
      non-perl tool that a particular module depends on.
    </p>
    <p>
      Here is a list of all the perl modules you might need. Some are essential, and some are only
      needed for tools that many exercises will not use. <c>Carp</c> <c>Class::Accessor</c>
      <c>Class::Tiny</c> <c>Data::Dumper</c> <c>DBI</c> <c>Digest::MD5</c> <c>File::Copy</c>
      <c>File::Find</c> <c>File::Path</c> <c>File::Spec</c> <c>GD</c> <c>Getopt::Long</c>
      <c>HTML::Entities</c> <c>Locale::Maketext::Lexicon</c> <c>MIME::Base64</c> <c>Mojo::Base</c>
      <c>Mojo::IOLoop</c> <c>Mojo::DOM Mojo::JSON</c> <c>Opcode</c> <c>Pandoc</c> <c>Perl::Tidy</c>
      <c>Pod::Simple::Search</c> <c>Scalar::Util</c> <c>Socket</c> <c>Tie::IxHash</c>
      <c>UUID::Tiny</c> <c>YAML::XS</c>. If you don't have one of these that is needed, and you
      attempt to process <webwork/> problems using local PG processing, you will get a clear
      message about which module is missing that you must pursue installing it.
    </p>
    <p>
      Here are some Linux package collections that we think are sufficient (but please report if
      you find them to be insufficient).
      <dl>
        <li>
          <title>Debian/Ubuntu</title>
          <p>
              <c>liblocale-maketext-lexicon-perl</c>, <c>libyaml-libyaml-perl</c>,
              <c>libuuid-tiny-perl</c>, <c>libclass-tiny-perl</c>, <c>libdbi-perl</c>,
              <c>libgd-perl</c>, <c>libgd-text-perl</c>
          </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <title>RedHat</title>
          <p>
              List not yet gathered. Please report if you put together a good list.
          </p>
        </li>
      </dl>
    </p>
    <p>
      To try to install using <c>cpanm</c>, of course first you must have <c>cpanm</c>. Try
      <c>cpanm --version</c> to see if you have it. If not, follow installation instructions for
      <url href="https://manpages.ubuntu.com/manpages/trusty/man3/App::cpanminus.3pm.html" visual="manpages.ubuntu.com/manpages/trusty/man3/App::cpanminus.3pm.html">Ubuntu</url>,
      <url href="https://packages.debian.org/search?keywords=cpanminus" visual="packages.debian.org/search?keywords=cpanminus">Debian</url>
      (<c>sudo apt install cpanminus</c>), RedHat (<c>sudo dnf install perl-CPAN</c>), or MacOS
      (<c>brew install cpanminus</c>, requiring you first install
      <url href="https://brew.sh/" visual="https://brew.sh/">Homebrew</url>). Or you could install
      <c>cpanm</c> directly following
      <url href="https://metacpan.org/pod/App::cpanminus" visual="metacpan.org/pod/App::cpanminus">these instruction</url>.
    </p>
    <p>
      Once you have <c>cpanm</c>, you can opt to install the above modules one at a time, or all at
      once. Either way, it is probably adequate to install the modules as your own user. And yet we
      will recommend that you install the modules as root to avoid certain installation headaches
      and so that your system is set up to use <c>webwork2</c> if that is ever desired. To install
      one at time, run commands like: <c>sudo cpanm Carp</c>. But proceed through each module listed
      above. This will help you clearly see if there was an issue during installation. To install
      all at once: <c>sudo cpanm Carp Class::Accessor ... YAML::XS</c>, replacing the dots with the
      full list of modules above.
    </p>
    <p>
      One known bump in the road may come with the <c>GD</c> module. You may need to actually
      install <c>gd</c> first, which is not a perl module. The perl <c>GD</c> module is the perl
      bridge to <c>gd</c>. For Ubuntu/Debian, install these packages: <c>pkgconf</c>, <c>gdlib</c>
      <c>libgd-dev</c>.
    </p>
    <p>
      Now in a publisher file, you can set the <tag>webwork</tag> element to have
      <attr>static-processing</attr> with value <c>local</c>. If you put the <c>pg</c> repository
      in the default location, this is all you need to do. Otherwise, you also need to add the
      attribute <attr>pg-location</attr> with the absolute path, for example <c>/opt/webwork/pg</c>.
      And when you process <webwork/> exercises for static representations (following
      <xref ref="webwork-representations"/>) your local copy of PG will be used instead of some
      remote server.
    </p>
    <p>
      Note that you will still need a network connection for problems in your HTML output to render
      as live interactive exercises.
    </p>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="webwork-server-configuration">
    <title>Configuring a <webwork/> Server for <pretext/></title>
    <p>
      To make use of <webwork/> in your <pretext/> project, you need a <webwork/> server.
      If someone is providing a <webwork/> server for you, like the AIM server
      at <url href="https://webwork-ptx.aimath.org" visual="webwork-ptx.aimath.org"/>,
      then we assume they have already configured that server for use with <pretext/>,
      and you may skip this section and move on to <xref ref="webwork-processing">Section</xref>.
    </p>
    <p>
      If you are configuring your own <webwork/> server to use with <pretext/>,
      we assume a mild familiarity with administrating a <webwork/> server.
      The version of <webwork/> needs to be 2.16 or later for use with <pretext/>.
    </p>
    <p>
      The only thing you need to do at this level is set the web server to use certain headers on content that is fetched.
      These headers tell a web browser that you are authorizing it to display content from this web server
      as embedded content inside pages from another web server (in particular, where you are hosting you <pretext/> book).
    </p>
    <p>
      In <c>webwork2/conf/</c> there should be the apache configuration file <c>webwork-apache2.4-config</c>.
      This file needs to include the lines:
    </p>
    <pre>
      <![CDATA[
      <IfModule mod_headers.c>
          <Location /webwork2/html2xml>
              Header set Access-Control-Allow-Origin "*"
          </Location>
          <Location /webwork2_files>
              Header set Access-Control-Allow-Origin "*"
          </Location>
      </IfModule>
      ]]>
    </pre>
    <p>
      Note there is the distribution file <c>webwork-apache2.4-config.dist</c>,
      which has these lines (or similar lines) commented out.
    </p>
    <p>
      If you are certain that your <pretext/> book will only be hosted at one site,
      (or if you are supporting multiple books, that they will only be hosted at one site)
      then you should consider replacing the <c>*</c>s above with that site (for example <c>https://mybook.myschool.edu</c>).
      This will mildly defend against unauthorized use of your <webwork/> server.
      It will make it so that if there are HTML pages at some other domain and they embed <webwork/> problems
      that rely on your <webwork/> server, then web browsers will refuse to load the embedded content.
    </p>
    <p>
      You may also need to enable headers by executing something like <c>sudo a2enmod headers</c> from the command line.
    </p>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="webwork-course-configuration">
    <title>Configuring a <webwork/> Course for <pretext/></title>
    <p>
      To make use of <webwork/> in your <pretext/> project, you need a host <webwork/> course.
      If someone is providing a <webwork/> server for you, like the AIM server
      at <url href="https://webwork-ptx.aimath.org" visual="webwork-ptx.aimath.org"/>,
      then we assume they have already configured a course for use with <pretext/>,
      and you may skip this section and move on to <xref ref="webwork-processing">Section</xref>.
    </p>
    <p>
      If you are configuring your own <webwork/> server to use with <pretext/>,
      we assume a mild familiarity with administrating a <webwork/> server.
      The version of <webwork/> needs to be 2.16 or later for use with <pretext/>.
    </p>
    <p>
      Using the <c>admin</c> course, create a course named <c>anonymous</c>.
      (You could name it something else, but we assume the name is <c>anonymous</c> in this guide.)
      In the course's Course Configuration menu, set all permissions to <c>admin</c>
      (or perhaps set some to the even more restrictive <c>nobody</c>).
      Except set <q>Allowed to login to the course</q> to <c>login_proctor</c>.
      Also if your server is new enough, it has <q>Allowed to view course home page</q> which should
      also be set to <c>login_proctor</c>.
    </p>
    <p>
      In the Classlist Editor, add a user named <c>anonymous</c> (again, you could use some other name),
      and set that user's permission level to <c>login_proctor</c>, the permission level one higher than <c>student</c>.
      Set that user's password to <c>anonymous</c> (again, you could use some other password).
      Note that because this is public information, anyone will be able to log into this course as this user.
      This is why restricting permissions in the previous paragraph is very important.
    </p>
    <p>
      Add the following lines to the <c>course.conf</c> file (which lives in the parent folder of the <c>templates/</c> folder.)
    </p>
    <pre>
      # Hide message about previewing hints and solutions for instructors
      $pg{specialPGEnvironmentVars}{ALWAYS_SHOW_HINT_PERMISSION_LEVEL} = 100;
      $pg{specialPGEnvironmentVars}{ALWAYS_SHOW_SOLUTION_PERMISSION_LEVEL} = 100;
    </pre>
    <p>
      In the <c>templates/macros/</c> folder, edit <c>PGcourse.pl</c> (or create it if need be) and add the following lines.
    </p>
    <pre>
      #### Replace essay boxes with a message
      my $essay_message = 'If you were logged into a WeBWorK course '
          . 'and this problem were assigned to you, '
          . 'you would be able to submit an essay answer '
          . 'that would be graded later by a human being.';

      sub essay_box {
        my $out = MODES(
          TeX => '',
          Latex2HTML => '',
          HTML => qq!&lt;p>$essay_message&lt;/p>!,
          PTX => '',
        );
        $out;
      };

      sub explanation_box {
        return if ($envir{waiveExplanations});
        my $out = MODES(
          TeX => '',
          Latex2HTML => '',
          HTML => qq!&lt;p>$essay_message&lt;/p>!,
          PTX => '',
        );
        $out;
      };

      #### Suppress essay help link
      sub essay_help {};

      #### How many attempts until hint is available
      $showHint = -1;
      # May be a bug that WeBWorK requires -1 instead of 0
      # for immediate access to hints

      1;
    </pre>
    <p>
      Now <pretext/> will be able to communicate with this course to retrieve what is needed.
    </p>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="webwork-pg-macros">
    <title>PG Macros from the <pretext/> Source</title>
    <p>
      The project's <webwork/> exercises may rely on PG macros that are written into the project's source.
      For example, the exercises might have TikZ images that rely on <tag>docinfo/latex-image-preamble</tag>.
    </p>
    <p>
      For this, a PG macro library file must be built and placed in the host course's <c>templates/macros/</c>
      folder <em>before</em> attempting to process the <webwork/> exercises. To build this macro library, run:
      <cd>
        pretext -c pg-macros aota.ptx
      </cd>
      <c>aota.ptx</c> in the example is the root file for your <pretext/> project.
      You could also specify a location to place the resulting macro library file:
      <cd>
        pretext -c pg-macros -d some/file/path aota.ptx
      </cd>
    </p>
    <p>
      Once you have the macro library file, upload it to the host <webwork/> course's <c>templates/macros</c> folder.
      If your project relies on the AIM <webwork/> server and you need to supply a macro library file
      to a host course on that server, post to <email>pretex-support@googlegroups.com</email> and we can help with that.
    </p>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="webwork-processing">
    <title>Processing <webwork/> Exercises</title>

    <subsection xml:id="webwork-representations">
      <title>Extraction and Processing</title>
      <p>
        Before anything else can be done, a <pretext/> project with <webwork/> problems must first have its <webwork/> content extracted and processed into multiple representations, which are then collected into an auxiliary XML file.
        Using the CLI, this is done with <c>pretext generate webwork</c> (if you want to reference a particular target, add <c>-t [targetname]</c>).
      </p>

      <p>
        If instead you want to use the <c>pretext/pretext</c> script, you might need to install the Python <c>requests</c> module.
        It is not uncommon for your computer to not have <c>requests</c> installed (although it comes with the CLI),
        so you should check if it is there and install it if need be.
        You can check if it is installed from the command line with:
        <cd>
          python -c "import requests"
        </cd>
        And if it isn't, you can install it with <c>pip</c>, specifically with:
        <cd>
          pip install requests
        </cd>
        (If you don't have <c>pip</c> installed, you could use:
        <cd>
          easy_install pip
        </cd>
        to install it.)
      </p>
      <p>
        Processing <webwork/> problems is best accomplished if you are using directory management.
        With a publication file, declare the external and generated directories as describe in
        <xref ref="processing-directory-management"/>.
        Then use the <c>pretext</c> script to extract <pretext/> content from the <webwork/> server.
        It will be placed in a <c>webwork</c> subfolder of your generated folder.
        For example:
      </p>
      <console>
        <input prompt="$ ">pretext -c webwork -p &lt;publisher&gt; aota.ptx</input>
      </console>
      <p>
        <c>aota.ptx</c> in the example is the root file for your <pretext/> project.
      </p>
      <warning>
        <title>File Paths</title>
        <p>
          In the previous example and those that follow, you should specify paths as needed.
          For example, the <c>pretext</c> script is typically at <c>~/pretext/pretext/pretext</c>.
          And the <c>-p</c> option is specifying a publication file.
        </p>
      </warning>
      <p>
        <c>-c webwork</c> means you are processing the <webwork/> components.
      </p>
      <p>
        <c>-p</c> specifies the publication file, as described in <xref ref="publication-file-reference"/>.
        In the publication file, the element <tag>webwork</tag> may have attributes <attr>server</attr>,
        <attr>course</attr>, <attr>user</attr>, and <attr>password</attr>.
        If absent, these default to <c>https://webwork-ptx.aimath.org</c>, <c>anonymous</c>, <c>anonymous</c>,
        <c>anonymous</c>, and <c>anonymous</c> respectively. If you specify a server, you must correctly
        specify the protocol (<c>http</c> versus <c>https</c>). And it must be version 2.16 or later.
        Do not include a trailing slash.
      </p>
    </subsection>

    <subsection xml:id="webwork-html-output">
      <title>HTML output</title>

      <p>
        We assume you are using managed directories, and have <webwork/> representations file as above.  Build the HTML with <c>pretext build web</c>.
        You can also use <c>pretext/pretext</c> to build HTML. For example:
      </p>
      <console>
        <input prompt="$ ">pretext -c doc -f html -p &lt;publisher&gt; -d &lt;destination&gt; aota.ptx</input>
      </console>
      <p>
        <c>-p</c> specifies the publication file, as described in <xref ref="publication-file-reference"/>.
      </p>
      <p>
        <c>-d</c> specifies a folder to place all of the HTML output.
        If unspecified, this will be the current working directory.
      </p>
      <p>
          There are five publisher file entries which  control how a <webwork/> problem is realized within <init>HTML</init> output.  These are divided based on where the exercise (or project-like) resides: inline, within a division of exercises, within a reading questions division, within a worksheet, or if it is a project or similar.  If the class of problems is declared <c>dynamic</c>, then each problem has a button that readers can click to make the problem interactive.  Conversely, if the class of problems is declared <c>static</c>, then the problems render with a static preview.
        </p>
        <p>
          By default, inline exercises and project-like will be dynamic, under the assumption that these are meant to be worked as a reader works through the material.  The others will be static, under the assumption that they will be placed on a WeBWorK server where they will be worked for scores and grades.  See <xref ref="online-webwork-dynamism"/> for the precise syntax for these switches.
        </p>
      <p>
        If an exercise is subdivided into tasks, then by default they will only be revealed incrementally
        as the reader answers each one correctly. If you would like to have all tasks revealed from the start,
        then this option may be elected in the publication file (see <xref ref="publication-file-webwork-task-reveal"/>).
      </p>
    </subsection>

    <subsection xml:id="webwork-latex-output">
      <title><latex/> output</title>

      <p>
        We assume you are using managed directories, and have <webwork/> representations file as above.  Then build as normal with the CLI.  Or
        you may use <c>pretext/pretext</c> to build a <latex/> PDF. For example:
      </p>
      <console>
        <input prompt="$ ">pretext -c doc -f pdf -p &lt;publisher&gt; -d &lt;destination&gt; aota.ptx</input>
      </console>
      <p>
        <c>-p</c> specifies the publication file, as described in <xref ref="publication-file-reference"/>.
      </p>
      <p>
        <c>-d</c> specifies a folder to place the PDF output.
        If unspecified, this will be the current working directory.
      </p>
    </subsection>

    <subsection>
      <title>Creating Files for Uploading to <webwork/></title>

      <p>
        All of the <tag>webwork</tag> that you have written into your project can be <q>harvested</q>
        and put into their own <c>.pg</c> files by the <c>pretext</c> script.
        These files are created with a folder structure that follows the chunking scheme you specify.
        This process also creates set definition files (<c>.def</c>) for each chunk (say, for each section):
        one for inline exercises (checkpoints) and one for divisional exercises.
        For <tag>webwork</tag> problems that come from the <webwork/> server,
        the <c>.def</c> file will include them as well.
        This archiving process creates set header <c>.pg</c> files for each set definition.
      </p>
      <p>
        For example:
      </p>
      <console>
        <input prompt="$ ">xsltproc -stringparam publisher &lt;publisher&gt; pretext-ww-problem-sets.xsl aota.ptx</input>
      </console>
      <p>
        You may need to specify paths to these files.
      </p>
      <p>
        With a book, you can break up your problem set into multiple files according to a chosen depth of the hierarchy.  See <xref ref="common-chunking-options"/> for details on how to specify this.
      </p>
      <p>
        This creates a folder named after your book title,
        which has a folder tree with all of the <c>.pg</c> and <c>.def</c> files laid out according to your chunk level.
        You can compress this folder and upload it into an active <webwork/> course
        where you may then assign the sets to your students (and modify, as you like).
      </p>
    </subsection>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Unachievable Conversions</title>

    <p>
      By authoring <webwork/> problems within <pretext/> you do not need to learn all the ins and outs of <init>PGML</init> markup
      and you can concentrate on simply becoming proficient with <pretext/>.
      However, there are a few <pretext/> constructions which are not achievable in a <webwork/> problem
      for one reason or another.
      We list exceptions here, and also try to use source-checking tools to alert you to any differences.
      <ul>
        <li>
          <p>
            Anything that is the numbered target of a cross-reference, such as a figure,
            may not be inside a <webwork/> exercise.
            The exercise may go on to have a life of its own independent of its parent <pretext/> project,
            and then such a number makes no sense.
          </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>
            Certain aspects of specifying borders of a <pretext/> <tag>tabular</tag>
            are not realizable in a <init>PGML</init> table. Specifically,
            <ul>
              <li>
                <p>
                  Specifying column-specific top border attributes are not implemented.
                </p>
              </li>
              <li>
                <p>
                  Cell-specific bottom border attributes are not implemented.
                </p>
              </li>
              <li>
                <p>
                  <c>medium</c> and <c>major</c> table rule-thickness attributes will be handled as if they were <c>minor</c>.
                </p>
              </li>
            </ul>
          </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>
            When constructing a list (<tag>ul</tag> or <tag>ol</tag>)
            specifying some number of columns (using the <attr>cols</attr> attribute)
            will be ignored. PGML markup has no way to declare multicolumn lists.
          </p>
        </li>
      </ul>
    </p>
  </section>

</chapter>
