<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!--   This file is part of the documentation of PreTeXt      -->
<!--                                                          -->
<!--      PreTeXt Author's Guide                              -->
<!--                                                          -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 2013-2023  Robert A. Beezer                -->
<!-- See the file COPYING for copying conditions.             -->

<appendix xml:id="liblouis">
    <title>LibLouis</title>
    <idx>liblouis</idx>

    <introduction>
        <p><url href="https://liblouis.io"><c>liblouis</c></url> is an open-source library for low-level translation of phrases into braille, supporting many, many languages.  We rely on Python bindings for this library to translate all of the literary text (non-math) to braille for a document, so this is an essential piece of the pipeline.  Once installed, its use is transparent.  This appendix outlines two alternative installation methods, current as of 2025-12-19, on Linux, Mac, and Windows Subsystem for Linux.  Contributions of adjustments for other operating systems are welcome.</p>
    </introduction>

    <section xml:id="liblouis-system-pkg">
        <title>Installing as a system package</title>

        <p>
            For many operating systems, one may install the <c>liblouis</c> Python bindings as a system package.  For instance, on Debain/Ubuntu systems and Windows Subsystem for Linux, run
            <cd>
                <cline># sudo apt install python3-louis</cline>
            </cd>
            and on Mac
            <cd>
                <cline># brew install liblouis</cline>
            </cd>
            To test the bindings, the following should complete successfully in a Python interpreter
            <cd>
                <cline>>>> import louis</cline>
            </cd>
        </p>

        <p>
            If you are following best practices by using a <xref ref="python-virtual" text="custom">Python virtual environment</xref> for your <pretext/> project, you will need to give the environment access to system packages since <c>liblouis</c> is now installed as a system package.  You can do this when creating the virtual environment using
            <cd>
                <cline># python3 -m venv /path/to/venv --system-site-packages</cline>
            </cd>
            If you have an existing virtual environment configured for your <pretext/> project, you may alternatively edit one line in the file <c>pyvenv.cfg</c> in the virtual environment's main directory:
            <cd>
                <cline>include-system-site-packages = true</cline>
            </cd>
        </p>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="liblouis-source">
        <title>Installing from source</title>

        <p>While the <c>python3-louis</c> system package appears to be updated frequently, if you need a more recent version of <c>liblouis</c> or simply feel a little more adventurous, you may wish to install <c>liblouis</c> directly from source following these instructions:
        <ul>
            <li>
                <p>Download the <c>liblouis-X.YY.0.tar.gz</c> archive from the <url href="https://liblouis.io/downloads">downloads page</url>.  Releases are tracked at the <url href="https://github.com/liblouis/liblouis/releases">GitHub release page</url>.  The <c>liblouisutdml</c> package is not necessary.</p>
            </li>
            <li>
                <p><c>tar -xvf liblouis-X.YY.0.tar.gz</c> into a scratch directory like <c>/tmp</c>.</p>
            </li>
            <li>
                <p>Switch to being root (<c>sudo</c>) and <c>cd</c> into the directory created by the extraction.</p>
            </li>
            <li>
                <p>In your terminal run<cd>
                <cline># ./configure --enable-ucs4</cline>
                <cline># make</cline>
                <cline># make install</cline>
                </cd>The <q>ucs4</q> flag enables 32-bit Unicode support, which is necessary for running tests later.</p>
            </li>
            <li>
                <p>Read <c>/tmp/liblouis-X.YY.0/python/README.md</c> and perform two steps, still as root, from within the directory structure in <c>/tmp</c>: install the bindings into your Python distribution and run the Python tests.  Instructions for setting up a Python virtual environment are also available in that file.</p>
            </li>
            <li>
                <p>I do not do anything special to clean-up afterwards, and of course, my <c>/tmp</c> goes away on the next reboot.  I also do not do anything special when installing the next version, I just follow the same procedure as a fresh install.</p>
            </li>
        </ul></p>
    </section>
</appendix>
