<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!--   This file is part of the documentation of PreTeXt      -->
<!--                                                          -->
<!--      PreTeXt Author's Guide                              -->
<!--                                                          -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 2013-2023  Robert A. Beezer                -->
<!-- See the file COPYING for copying conditions.             -->

<appendix xml:id="liblouis">
    <title>LibLouis</title>
    <idx>liblouis</idx>

    <p><url href="https://liblouis.io"><c>liblouis</c></url> is an open-source library for low-level translation of phrases into braille, supporting many, many languages.  We rely on Python bindings for this library to translate all of the literary text (non-math) to braille for a document, so this is an essential piece of the pipeline.  Once installed, its use is transparent.  This appendix contains some brief notes to help with installation, current as of 2023-06-09, and for Ubuntu Linux 22.04.  Contributions of adjustments for other operating systems welcome.</p>

    <p><ul>
        <li>
            <p>Download the <c>liblouis-X.YY.0.tar.gz</c> archive from the <url href="https://liblouis.io/downloads">downloads page</url>.  Releases are tracked at the <url href="https://github.com/liblouis/liblouis/releases">GitHub release page</url>.  The <c>liblouisutdml</c> package is not necessary.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
            <p><c>tar -xvf liblouis-X.YY.0.tar.gz</c> into a scratch directory like <c>/tmp</c>.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
            <p>Switch to being root (<c>sudo</c>) and <c>cd</c> into the directory created by the extraction.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
            <p>In your terminal run<cd>
                <cline># ./configure --enable-ucs4</cline>
                <cline># make</cline>
                <cline># make install</cline>
            </cd>The <q>ucs4</q> flag enables 32-bit Unicode support, which is necessary for running tests later.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
            <p>Read <c>/tmp/liblouis-X.YY.0/python/README.md</c> and perform two steps, still as root, from within the directory structure in <c>/tmp</c>: install the bindings into your Python distribution and run the Python tests.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
            <p>I do not do anything special to clean-up afterwards, and of course, my <c>/tmp</c> goes away on the next reboot.  I also do not do anything special when installing the next version, I just follow the same procedure as a fresh install.</p>
        </li>
    </ul></p>
</appendix>
