<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!--   This file is part of the documentation of PreTeXt      -->
<!--                                                          -->
<!--      PreTeXt Author's Guide                              -->
<!--                                                          -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 2013-2016  Robert A. Beezer                -->
<!-- See the file COPYING for copying conditions.             -->

<appendix xml:id="offline-mathjax">
    <title>Offline MathJax</title>
    <idx>MathJax</idx>

    <introduction>
        <p><pretext/> uses the well-known <latex/> syntax for mathematics.  One fundamental reason for this choice is that the <url href="https://www.mathjax.org/" visual="www.mathjax.org/">MathJax</url> Javascript library is so capable at rendering <latex/> inside of an <init>HTML</init> web page.  Of course, it is not hard to render <latex/> syntax inside of <latex/> output!  But what about output formats that are not processed by <latex/> or Javascript, such as <init>EPUB</init> or braille?  That is where running MathJax offline (locally) comes into play.</p>
    </introduction>

    <section xml:id="install-mathjax">
        <title>MathJax and Speech Rule Engine</title>
        <idx>Speech Rule Engine</idx>

        <p>MathJax is packaged as a <c>node.js</c> program. A component of MathJax is Speech Rule Engine (<init>SRE</init>), which converts <latex/> to text that represents a spoken version of the mathematics, and to Nemeth braille, a braille code for expressing mathematics.</p>

        <p>Any <c>node.js</c> script requires installing Node. See <xref ref="node-and-npm"/> for instructions on doing so. Once Node is installed, you can use the following instructions to complete the installation of MathJax and the <init>SRE</init>.</p>

        <p>Follow the directions here <em>exactly</em>.  Do not free-style and think some modification will have a better or identical result.  In a terminal, set your working directory with<cd>
            <cline>cd /path/to/pretext/script/mjsre</cline>
        </cd>
        Install both packages at the same time with a single command:<cd>
            <cline>./update-sre</cline>
        </cd>It is possible you will need to make this simple script executable.  On Unix-style systems (Linux, Mac OS) this can be done with the <c>chmod</c> command.  As this is a bash script, Windows users must use Window's Subsystem for Linux or examine the contents of the script to run the commands manually.</p>

        <p>The <c>update-sre</c> script is supplied by <pretext/>.  It will create a file and a directory:<cd>
            <cline>/path/to/pretext/script/mjsre/package-lock.json</cline>
            <cline>/path/to/pretext/script/mjsre/node_modules</cline>
        </cd>Neither will be tracked by <c>git</c>.  Since SRE changes faster than MathJax, this will replace MathJax's expectation for a version of SRE with a potentially newer version.  So do not be alarmed if it appears MathJax is missing a dependency, that is intentional.</p>

        <p>Now you have copies of MathJax and SRE that can be used by the <c>pretext/pretext</c> script to process mathematics offline into useful formats for conversions to <init>EPUB</init>, Kindle, and braille.</p>
    </section>


    <section xml:id="math-representations">
        <title>Mathematics Representations</title>

        <p>Once MathJax is installed properly, the <c>pretext/pretext</c> script will be able to produce an <init>EPUB</init> version of your project.  The script will first analyze your document, isolating all of the mathematics.  These are then processed by MathJax and produce a file of <term>representations</term> of the mathematics, either as <init>SVG</init> images or as MathML versions.  These representations are then inserted properly into the eventual output.  This process is all automatic but explains why it is possible to produce two different types of <init>EPUB</init>.  A good test of your installation is to use the <c>pretext/pretext</c> script to make an <init>EPUB</init> (<xref provisional="epub production"/>) or the script can be used to simply produce structured files of these alternate representations (see <xref provisional="script math representations"/> or paragraph just below).</p>

        <p>With <init>SRE</init> also installed, text (speech) becomes a possible representation, as well as Nemeth braille.  This makes possible an <init>EPUB</init> version that is all text, and there are online sites that will turn this <init>EPUB</init> into an audio book (of not very good quality).  The braille representations are one component of the production of braille output.  (<xref provisional="braille production"/>, <xref ref="mathematics-representations" text="title"/>)</p>

        <p>If you use the <c>pretext/pretext</c> script with a <c>math</c> component, and a format of <c>svg</c> or <c>mathml</c>, you will produce a file of these representations, structured by <init>XML</init> (naturally).  These files are not much use by themselves, but may be of interest.</p>
    </section>

</appendix>
