<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!--   This file is part of the documentation of PreTeXt      -->
<!--                                                          -->
<!--      PreTeXt Author's Guide                              -->
<!--                                                          -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 2013-2016  Robert A. Beezer                -->
<!-- See the file COPYING for copying conditions.             -->

<appendix xml:id="python">
    <title>Python</title>

    <section xml:id="python-executable">
        <title>Python Executable</title>

        <p>While the majority of the processing of your text is accomplished with <init>XSL</init> transforms, we rely on Python for numerous other tasks and conveniences.  So, sooner or later, you will want, or need, to get Python working on your system.  Part of our attraction to Python is that is very popular and so should run very similarly (identically?) on a variety of systems: Linux, Mac, and Windows.  So the quicker we can get you to a platform-neutral setup, the better.</p>

        <p>On Linux and Mac, you will likely have at least some version of Python already installed.  On Windows, you may need to explicitly install it.  (We hope to provide some more careful advice here for Windows users.  For now, see <xref ref="installing-anaconda"/> and <xref ref="windows-subsystem-linux"/>.)</p>

        <p>Python 2 is no longer being developed and is officially dead.  That does not mean you do not have it on your system.  And for older systems, it may well be the default.  <pretext/> requires at least Python 3.8.5 (current as of 2022-08-31).  At a command-line, or in a terminal or console, or at a command-prompt, try<cd>
            <cline>python --version</cline>
        </cd>and if the result is unacceptable, then try<cd>
            <cline>python3 --version</cline>
        </cd>Remember which variant you need<mdash/>we will just routinely use the generic <c>python</c>.</p>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="python-virtual">
        <title>Python Virtual Environment</title>

        <p>There is a very good chance your system has a version of Python
        installed already since various other programs rely on it.  You will be much happier if various Python programs you need for <pretext/> do not get entangled with your Python programs installed as system software.  And if we need to help you debug some related problems we will ask you to work in a virtual environment anyway.  We will follow a <url href="https://realpython.com/python-virtual-environments-a-primer/" visual="realpython.com/python-virtual-environments-a-primer/">primer</url> that has been recommended by Brad Miller, founder of Runestone Interactive.  See that page for more details.</p>

        <p>These are condensed instructions without much explanation.<ol>
            <li>Do not install the old-school <c>virtualenv</c> module.</li>
            <li>Make a directory anywhere you like named <c>virtual-python</c> and change into it.</li>
            <li><c>python3 -m venv ptx</c> makes a virtual environment named <c>ptx</c>. (Requires Python 3.6 or later.)</li>
        </ol>Done.  But how do you use it?<ol>
            <li>
                <p>To activate your virtual environment, be sure you are in the <c>virtual-python</c> directory.
                For Mac or Linux, with a bash shell go<cd>
                    <cline>source ptx/bin/activate</cline>
                    <cline>(ptx) $</cline>
                </cd>
                There are other scripts for other shells, take a look around.</p>
                <p>For Windows, go<cd>
                    <cline>ptx/Scripts/activate.bat</cline>
                    <cline>(ptx) &gt;</cline>
                </cd>Notice that your prompt has changed to remind you that now anything you do with Python will be <q>sandboxed</q> in this virtual environment and not get mixed up with your system Python.</p>
            </li>
            <li>Now you can do any Python-related task using your virtual environment, and can change directories if desired.</li>
            <li>
                <p>When you are finished with your virtual environment, on Mac or Linux with a bash shell you simply go<cd>
                    <cline>(ptx) $ deactivate</cline>
                    <cline>$</cline>
                </cd></p>
                <p>For Windows, similarly<cd>
                    <cline>(ptx) &gt; deactivate</cline>
                    <cline>&gt;</cline>
                </cd></p>
                <p>We have one report, on a Mac, of deactivation dropping you into a different virtual environment named <c>(base)</c>.  A way to leave that virtual environment is to run<cd>
                    <cline>(base) $ conda deactivate</cline>
                </cd>This appears to be due to Anaconda somehow creating a default base environment initially.  If you have this experience and find a simple solution, please report it.  Some details at <url href="https://stackoverflow.com/questions/54429210/how-do-i-prevent-conda-from-activating-the-base-environment-by-default" visual="stackoverflow.com/questions/54429210">Stack Overflow 54429210</url> may be helpful.</p>
            </li>
        </ol></p>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="pip-install">
        <title><init>PIP</init> Install</title>

        <p><init>PIP</init>, in the open source tradition of recursive acronyms,
        stands for <q>PIP Installs Packages</q>.  This package manager helps you obtain software and keep it up-to-date.  There are three packages that are indispensable for use with <pretext/> so you can practice doing installations now via your virtual environment.</p>

        <p>
          If you have installed the <pretext/>-CLI already using pip, then all the programs below are already installed.  Otherwise (for example, if you are using <c>xsltproc</c>) you will need to install the following manually.
        </p>

        <p>
          To install all required additional python libraries, in your virtual environment, navigate to the <c>pretext</c> directory and run
          <cd>
            <cline>(ptx) $ pip install</cline>
          </cd>
          You can also install individual libraries, as in
          <cd>
            <cline>(ptx) $ pip install lxml</cline>
          </cd>
        </p>

        <p>With <c>lxml</c>, you have a collection of Python routines that interface with the same base libraries for <init>XSL</init> processing as the <c>xsltproc</c> executable.  A second library is <c>requests</c> which moderates communications with online servers and is necessary to communicate with WeBWorK servers and with a YouTube server that provides thumbnail images for static versions of videos. The <c>pdfCropMargins</c> package provides a tool that will crop images during their production with the <c>pretext</c> script.  The <c>pyMuPDF</c> library then converts the <init>PDF</init> that was cropped to <init>SVG</init> and <init>PNG</init> images.  Finally, <c>playwright</c> uses a Chromium headless browser to take static screenshots of interactive elements of your project.</p>

        <p>Note that right after you install <c>playwright</c> then you want to run<cd>
            <cline> playwright install</cline>
        </cd>one time only.  This will install three web browsers (Chromium, Firefox, WebKit) and FFMPEG where they should only be available to this package.</p>

        <table>
            <title>PIP-installable Python Packages</title>

            <tabular>
                <col/>
                <col width="60%"/>
                <row bottom="major">
                    <cell>Package</cell>
                    <cell>Purpose</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell><c>lxml</c></cell>
                    <cell><p>XSL processing</p></cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell><c>requests</c></cell>
                    <cell><p>Communication with online servers</p></cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell><c>pdfCropMargins</c></cell>
                    <cell><p>Crop images during production</p></cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell><c>playwright</c></cell>
                    <cell><p>Automatic screenshots of interactive elements</p></cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell><c>pyMuPDF</c></cell>
                    <cell><p>Convert images to SVG and PNG</p></cell>
                </row>
            </tabular>
        </table>
    </section>
</appendix>
