<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!--   This file is part of the documentation of PreTeXt      -->
<!--                                                          -->
<!--      PreTeXt Author's Guide                              -->
<!--                                                          -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 2013-2016  Robert A. Beezer                -->
<!-- See the file COPYING for copying conditions.             -->

<appendix xml:id="schema-install">
    <title>Schema Tools</title>

    <introduction>
        <p>This appendix has technical information about tools that work with the <acro>RELAX-NG</acro> schema and our additional validation stylesheet.  See <xref ref="schema" /> for a more general overview.</p>
    </introduction>

    <section xml:id="jing-trang">
        <title>Jing and Trang</title>

        <introduction>
            <p>These tools come from James Clark, an author of the <acro>RELAX-NG</acro> syntax.  <c>trang</c> is a converter between different formats for schemas.  An author should not ever need it.  Though a <pretext /> developer might find it useful, and it is a by-product of the <c>jing-trang</c> install described below.</p>

            <p><c>jing</c> is our recommendation for <acro>RELAX-NG</acro> validation by authors, and works very well.</p>

            <p><c>jing</c> and <c>trang</c> are packaged (separately) for Debian/Ubuntu Linux, see <xref ref="jing-ubuntu"/>.  Reports of other similarly easy installations for other operating systems, to be included here, are especially welcome.  We have employed the Debian/Ubuntu versions and also versions built from source, see <xref ref="jing-from-source"/>.</p>
        </introduction>

        <subsection xml:id="jing-ubuntu">
            <title><c>jing</c> on Ubuntu and CoCalc</title>

            <p><url href="https://cocalc.com/" visual="cocalc.com/">CoCalc</url> runs Ubuntu when you create a terminal window.  The necessary Ubuntu Linux (Debian) package is also named <c>jing</c> and is installed as part of the CoCalc setup.  So on Ubuntu, you need to install this package, and on CoCalc you will need to copy over the <c>schema/pretext.rng</c> version of the schema.  If you have a CoCalc subscription, it would be even better if you made a clone of the PreTeXt repository, so it would be trivial to update and always have the latest version of the schema in your CoCalc account.</p>

            <p>Now it is straightforward to execute <c>jing</c>:<cd>
                <cline>jing /path/to/pretext.rng aota.xml</cline>
            </cd></p>

            <p>Presumably something similar to the above will work for any Linux distribution that has packages for <c>jing</c>.</p>

            <!-- warning about using single source also in "from source" section -->
            <p>Note that if you have modularized your source files (see <xref ref="processing-modular"/>), you only need to provide the top-level file as an argument to <c>jing</c>. In particular, the subsidiary files are certain to fail validation since they do not have a <tag>pretext</tag> root element.</p>
        </subsection>

        <subsection xml:id="jing-from-source">
            <title>Install <c>jing</c> from Source</title>

            <p>If you cannot install this tool easily as part of your system, you can still follow the notes below to build from source.  Many authors have done this successfully.  Installation notes for <c>jing</c> and <c>trang</c> follow.
                <dl width="narrow">
                    <li>
                        <title>Clone</title>
                        <p>Clone the <c>git</c> repository at <url href="https://github.com/relaxng/jing-trang" visual="github.com/relaxng/jing-trang"/> with the command<cd>
                            <cline>git clone https://github.com/relaxng/jing-trang</cline>
                        </cd>which assumes you have a command-line version of <c>git</c> installed.  You will end up with a new <c>jing-trang</c> directory, which you will certainly want <em>outside</em> of your <pretext /> files and <em>outside</em> of your project files.</p>
                    </li>

                    <li>
                        <title><c>readme.md</c></title>
                        <p>Follow the instructions in the <c>readme.md</c> found at the top level of the <c>jing-trang</c> distribution, observing the following notes keyed to the four steps.  These helpful notes come courtesy of the experiences of Jahrme Risner, Mitch Keller, Bruce Yoshiwara, Ken Levasseur, and Jessica Sklar on a variety of operating systems.</p>
                        <p><ol>
                            <li>
                                <p>It is necessary to have a developer's version of <c>java</c> on your machine.  Try <c>which java</c> to see if one is already available.  Any output here might help in the next step.  References here to the <init>JDK</init> is the Java Development Kit.  There are specific directions for MacOS (<xref ref="mac-os-java"/>) and Windows (<xref ref="section-jing"/>).</p>
                            </li>

                            <li>
                                <p>You will need to have the <c>JAVA_HOME</c> environment variable set correctly.  You can try <c>echo ${JAVA_HOME}</c> in a Linux console to see if it produces anything sensible and/or consistent with Step 1.  Ken Levasseur notes that on MacOS you can go<cd>
                                    <cline>echo $(/usr/libexec/java_home)</cline>
                                </cd>and the output is what you set to the <c>JAVA_HOME</c> variable.</p>
                                <p>On Windows you may need to set Environmental Variables in the Windows System Properties GUI, both here and in Step 4.</p>
                            </li>

                            <li>
                                <p>Setting your working directory to the root directory of the <c>jing-trang</c> distribution should not cause any particular difficulties.</p>
                            </li>

                            <li>
                                <p>You may need to install the <c>ANT</c> tool, almost certainly on Windows.  Again, on Windows you may need to set an <c>ANT_HOME</c> environment variable.  On Linux, this may be all set for you already as a system tool.</p>
                                <p>The README suggests changing slashes on Windows.  But you may already be using a shell that gives Unix-like behavior.  So try both directions, if necessary.  Also, the README suggests running <c>./ant test</c> (or <c>.\ant test</c>). Doing this on Windows may yield a <c>BUILD FAILED</c> message, but <c>jing</c> may still work.</p>
                            </li>
                        </ol></p>
                    </li>

                    <li>
                        <title>Results</title>
                        <p>Change into the <c>build</c> subdirectory.  You may have more files here, but the two you really want are <c>jing.jar</c> and <c>trang.jar</c>.  So if you have these, you are in good shape.</p>
                        <p>If you have modularized your source files (<xref ref="processing-modular" />) then you need one more library.  Look in the top-level <c>lib</c> directory (a peer of <c>build</c>) for <c>xercesImpl.jar</c>.  You have two and a half choices now.<ul>
                            <li>Copy <c>lib/xercesImpl.jar</c> into <c>build</c>.</li>
                            <li>Or make a <q>symbolic link</q> to the third JAR archive.  Be sure you are in <c>build</c> and go<cd>
                                <cline>ln -s ../lib/xercesImpl.jar</cline>
                            </cd>which will just make your operating system think this third archive is in the <c>build</c> directory.</li>
                            <li>A third option would be to adjust/augment some classpath information below and send us a report of success.  We have not tested this approach.</li>
                        </ul></p>
                    </li>
                </dl>
            </p>

            <p>Now you are ready to use <c>jing</c> to validate a <pretext /> document.  Note that the commands below require the <init>XML</init> version of the schema, which is the non-compact version.  Also, these are the commands if you build <c>jing-trang</c> from source.  If you install a system-supplied version, then consult the <c>man</c> pages, or similar, for syntax which is likely much easier and direct.</p>

            <!-- warning about using single source also in "ubuntu/cocalc" version -->
            <p>For a document contained in a single file, run (with suitable working directory and path prefixes).<cd>
                <cline>java -jar jing-trang/build/jing.jar pretext.rng my-book.xml</cline>
            </cd>For a document modularized across several files using the <c>xinclude</c> mechanism, issue as one single command line (again, with suitable working directory and path prefixes).  This presumes you have moved or symlinked the <c>lib/xercesImpl.jar</c> file into the <c>build</c> directory.  Do not leave any spaces around the equals-sign, we have split that line there for readability, so the <c>-D</c> option should not have any spaces in its argument.<cd>
                <cline>java -classpath jing-trang/build</cline>
                <cline>-Dorg.apache.xerces.xni.parser.XMLParserConfiguration=</cline>
                <cline>    org.apache.xerces.parsers.XIncludeParserConfiguration</cline>
                <cline>-jar jing-trang/build/jing.jar pretext.rng my-book.xml</cline>
            </cd>It may go without saying that scripting this task will make you more likely to do it as often as is necessary and you will save yourself much time, and a little frustration, in the process.</p>

            <p>Jahrme Risner provides the following setup he uses to make it very convenient to regularly validate his sources.  This is a <q>shell script</q>, which a Linux user might add to their <c>~/.bashrc</c> file.  Note that we have again split the line with the <c>-D</c> option at the equals-sign, without a line-continuation character.  Do not do that in your version.<cd>
                <cline>ptx-check() {</cline>
                <cline>  java\</cline>
                <cline>    -classpath ~/GitHub/jing-trang/build\</cline>
                <cline>    -Dorg.apache.xerces.xni.parser.XMLParserConfiguration=</cline>
                <cline>        org.apache.xerces.parsers.XIncludeParserConfiguration\</cline>
                <cline>    -jar ~/GitHub/jing-trang/build/jing.jar\</cline>
                <cline>    ~/GitHub/pretext/Schema/pretext.rng "$1"</cline>
                <cline>}</cline>
            </cd>Then he can simply go<cd>
                <cline>~ $ ptx-check my-book.xml</cline>
            </cd>at anytime.  Note that you might have to provide or adjust some of the paths above for your situation.  And there are other ways to script tasks like this.</p>
        </subsection>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="pretext-validation-plus">
        <title><pretext/> Validation Plus</title>

        <p>The second step of validation is our <q>validation-plus</q> stylesheet.  Fortunately, there is nothing to install.  Use it just like the conversions you have already been doing.  In the <pretext/> distribution, in the <c>schema</c> directory you will find <c>pretext-validation-plus.xsl</c>.  This is a stylesheet, unique to <pretext/>, which will carefully analyze your source to find any exceptions that the <acro>RELAX-NG</acro> schema was not designed to catch.  You use the stylesheet like any other,<cd>
            <cline>xsltproc ~/pretext/schema/pretext-validation-plus.xsl ~/books/aota/animals.xml</cline>
        </cd>with suitably adjusted paths, and be sure to provide the <c>-xinclude</c> switch if your source is modularized across multiple files (<xref ref="processing-modular" />).  No news is good news, but each exception found should provide enough explanation for you to locate, and correct, the problem.  These messages are under <pretext/>'s control, so please report any that are not helpful enough.  That's it<mdash/>easy.</p>
    </section>


</appendix>
