<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!--   This file is part of the documentation of PreTeXt      -->
<!--                                                          -->
<!--      PreTeXt Author's Guide                              -->
<!--                                                          -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 2013-2018  Robert A. Beezer                -->
<!-- See the file COPYING for copying conditions.             -->

<appendix xml:id="welcome">
    <title>Welcome to the <pretext/> Community</title>

    <introduction>
        <p>Thank-you for your interest in <pretext/>, and welcome!  This appendix is meant to answer some questions you may have about how this open-source project is organized, how you can get help, and how you can contribute back.</p>

        <p><pretext/> is not <latex/> and it is not Word.  Some <q>features</q> of those languages are intentionally missing, but more importantly, the mind-set expected of authors is completely different. One of the most important distinctions is that <pretext/> treats the author, the publisher, and the reader (which might be an instructor) as separate entities<mdash/>even when those are all the same person.</p>

        <p>Newcomers to <pretext/> should focus on the author role. Make sure the structure of your book is marked-up properly. If something looks wrong in your output, assume it is a problem with the source markup.  If the source is correct but the output does not look as you wish, leave that as a problem for the publisher, to be addressed <em>after</em> you have finished writing the content.</p>
    </introduction>

    <section xml:id="help-and-support">
        <title>Help and Support</title>

        <p>There is a documentation area at the project website.  Presumably, that is where you found this <pubtitle><pretext/> Guide</pubtitle>.  This is what another software project might call the <pubtitle>User's Manual</pubtitle>.  So start here.  Re-read <xref ref="philosophy"/> on the project philosophy and the principles in <xref ref="list-principles"/> at regular intervals.  <xref ref="overview"/> is meant to inform you of the features of <pretext/>, without getting into all the details.  It will frequently refer you to <xref ref="topics"/> for all those details.</p>

        <p>PreTeXt is fundamentally a specification of a set of elements and attributes, a topic discussed in <xref ref="schema"/>.  This chapter also discusses validation.  Once comfortable, but before authoring lots of material, take the time to get validation working, and use it regularly.  Do not save it for last.</p>

        <p>There are many examples available in an area on the website.  Compare <pretext /> source to the resulting output (in both directions).  The <articletitle>sample article</articletitle> is not always pretty, since it is used for testing, but it does try to have one of everything.</p>

        <p>When the above is not sufficient, the <c>pretext-support</c> Google Group is the right place to ask questions.  If you are trying to determine which elements to use to accomplish something, provide some context.  Do not ask, <q>How do I print a line of text upside-down?</q>  Instead say, <q>I am writing a monograph on mammalian vision, and I'd like the reader to use a mirror to view a line of text written upside down.  What is the best way to do that?</q>  (I think the answer would be: make an image and include that, rather than trying to get reflected text.)  Sometimes a quick search of the Goggle Group may yield insights.  Overall, do your best not to be a <url href="http://slash7.com/2006/12/22/vampires/" visual="slash7.com/2006/12/22/vampires/">Help Vampire</url>.</p>

    </section>

    <section xml:id="drop-in">
        <title>Weekly Drop-Ins</title>

        <p>Since May<nbsp/>2020 there has been a standing weekly online gathering of <pretext/> authors and developers on Friday afternoons.  And now there is a companion session on Tuesday afternoons, and a Getting Started session on Mondays.  A weekly schedule of these, and other activities, is posted to the <c>pretext-announce</c> Google Group, so look there for particulars.   Once in a while there are scheduled discussions on development topics or seminars on topics of interest to authors and developers (such as building an index, see <xref ref="topic-index-advice"/>).  But mostly there is no agenda and no schedule.  Come late, leave early, drop-in, drop-out. If you are present, then you are implicitly available to help someone with questions, even if you are working on something yourself.  The rest of us may lurk and/or join in.  We can use break-out rooms if a subgroup wants to run a discussion, work on a targeted project, or help somebody get started one-on-one.  The model is the hotel lobby after dinner at a workshop, but you provide your own contraband.</p>

        <p>So this is a great place to discuss a support question (likely with the person who wrote the code!) or a place to get involved with development.</p>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="github-issues">
        <title>Feature Requests and Reporting Problems</title>

        <p>We use the <term>issue tracker</term> at the GitHub site as an organized to-do list.  You do not need to know anything about <c>git</c> to use this forum.  Just make a new issue, or make a comment on an existing issue.  Frequently, a discussion on the groups will culminate with the creation of a new issue.  It is nice to have a link from the discussion to the issue, and vice-versa.</p>

        <p>If you are asked to create an issue in response to a discussion you initiated, please consider doing so.  It will save the other volunteers just a bit of time to work on other parts of <pretext />.  And you will also get email-for-life as the issue is discussed and eventually closed.  It is a very helpful contribution.</p>

        <p>As you gain more experience, you will identify bugs, obsolete instructions, typos, <etc/>  Search the issues to see if there is something relevant you can add.  For example, your particular version of a bug might provide the key insight into identifying the cause.  When you are certain something is wrong, and there is no need to discuss it in the groups, feel free to go straight to making an issue.  For something like a list of typos, make a single issue and just keep editing your initial post.</p>

        <p>If you have some structural problem, see if you can reproduce it by adding into the minimal example, and post that <em>entire</em> source file.  If the rendering in <init>HTML</init> is a bit off or you think it exhibits a bug, be sure to post a link to a <em>live</em> example, not just a verbal description and <em>definitely not</em> a screenshot.  If you need an easy, quick, free, temporary location to host one file or your whole project as <init>HTML</init>, try <url href="https://app.netlify.com/drop" visual="app.netlify.com/drop">Netlify Drop</url>.</p>

        <!-- Sean Fitzpatrick suggestion, 2024-10-02 -->
        <p>If you are posting code snippets, and copying out of an editor using Dark Mode, try <c>ctrl-shift-V</c> when you paste and perhaps the Dark Mode color scheme will go away<mdash/>making it easier for some to read.</p>
    </section>


    <section xml:id="contributing">
        <title>Contributing</title>

        <p>As a project that is licensed openly, we welcome contributions.  And this does not necessarily mean you need to learn our primary language, <init>XSL</init>.  For ideas, find the issues on GitHub that have the label <c>contributor project</c>.  As one example, it would be very helpful if a member of the community would create and maintain a Wikipedia page.  That is a skill that is very distinct from the other skills used to create and maintain other parts of the project.  See <url href="https://github.com/PreTeXtBook/pretext/issues/207" visual="github.com/PreTeXtBook/pretext/issues/207">Issue #207</url>.</p>

        <p>The documentation is authored in <pretext/>, so you know how to create additions, clean-up obsolete parts, and fix typos.  If you know <c>git</c> and GitHub, then a pull request (on a new branch!) is a very economical way for us to manage contributions.  Even if you do not know GitHub, we can easily accept files written in <pretext/> that contain changes to the documentation.  For example, files supporting localization to new languages (see <xref ref="topic-localization"/>) are ideal for simply submitting an entire file.  (Send files to us by email, or post as attachments on one of the Google groups.)</p>

        <p>Conversions are written in <init>XSL</init>, a declarative language.  It has a steep learning curve, but is very powerful for an application like this.  Start small, and we do not mind helping you along with suggestions and critiques.  Do not, do not, begin an ambitious task unless your skills are up to it.</p>

        <p>When you have gained significant experience as an author, and have a good feel for the questions asked by other authors due to your material participation in the <c>pretext-support</c> group, then it may be time to apply to be part of the <c>pretext-dev</c> group.  This where design discussions are held and nasty bugs are squashed collectively.</p>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="personal-email">
        <title>Personal Email</title>

        <p>How do we put this politely?  Personal email to the core <pretext/> developers should be your last resort.  We are not unfriendly<mdash/>just the opposite.  We would love to hear from you, but in the groups.  Here is the rationale:<ul>
            <li>You may get a better answer from somebody who is not the most active developer, but understands your particular need better than anybody else.  You will never get that answer with a personal email.</li>
            <li>Developers teach university courses, travel to professional meetings, sleep at night, take naps, turn off their email for big coding pushes, and sometimes travel in the wilderness and are offline for days at a time.  You are likely to get quick responses from the core developers through the groups, but if they are not available a personal email may get a slower response.  (I am inclined to answer posts on the groups before I work through personal email.)</li>
            <li>Many contributors prefer to provide help in a public forum because their efforts are then more widely recognized.</li>
            <li>Your question and its answer are searchable by others.  (The groups and issues are public.)  A personal email is no help to anybody else.</li>
            <li>We prefer to make as many decisions as possible <em>openly</em>.  So a discussion on a public group or site is there for all to see, now and later.</li>
            <li>We depend on granting agencies for much of our funding.  Membership in groups, forks on GitHub, activity in the groups, number of issues, and number of contributors to the repository, are all crude measures of the health of the project.  Personal emails add nothing to those measures.</li>
            <li>Everybody who has committed their big writing project to <pretext/> likes to see an active, responsive, friendly community supporting its use and growth.  Just by asking a necessary question, you can add to that community.</li>
        </ul></p>

        <p>We understand that nobody likes to pop their head up and ask a <q>stupid question.</q>  But it is counterproductive to do personally what we can do better collectively.  The groups are friendly forums (we will enforce that if we ever have to) and everybody there made an initial post once.  And the group members largely enjoy sharing their advice, experience, and knowledge.  So, please make a contribution simply by saving the personal emails for that which is really personal.  Thanks, and we'll look forward to chatting with you on the groups!</p>
    </section>

</appendix>
