<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>

<!--   This file is part of the documentation of PreTeXt      -->
<!--                                                          -->
<!--      PreTeXt Author's Guide                              -->
<!--                                                          -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 2013-2016  Robert A. Beezer                -->
<!-- See the file COPYING for copying conditions.             -->

<appendix xml:id="windows-cli">
  <title>Installing the <pretext/>-CLI on Windows</title>
  <author>Sean Fitzpatrick</author>

  <introduction>
    <p>
      The <pretext/>-CLI is the simplest way for authors to get started using <pretext/>,
      and it is the recommended method on all systems, including Windows.
      Details on using the CLI can be found starting in <xref ref="processing-CLI"/>.
      Setting up the <pretext/>-CLI on Windows is considerably simpler than the method presented in <xref ref="windows-install-notes"/>,
      but there is still some effort required.
      In particular, you will have to install several pieces of software to get your system ready for using <pretext/>.
    </p>

    <p>
      If you prefer a video walkthrough, one is provided below.
      The video is approximately 40 minutes in length, but it goes through the entire installation process,
      from adding the necessary software, to setting up <url href="https://github.com" visual="github.com">GitHub</url>.
    </p>

    <video youtube="tAtdzyVBcZA" preview="yt-windows-cli.png"/>
  </introduction>

  <section xml:id="windows-cli-software">
    <title>Software prerequisites</title>
    <introduction>
      <p>
        We begin with the programs you will want to have installed prior to using the <pretext/>-CLI.
        All software can be downloaded free of charge, and is relatively easy to install.
      </p>
    </introduction>

    <subsection xml:id="windows-cli-vscode">
      <title>VSCode</title>
      <p>
        <term>VSCode</term> is short for Visual Studio Code.
        This is a text editor developed by Microsoft; we recommend it not because it plays well with Windows (although it does),
        but because of the availability of the <c>pretext-tools</c> add-on, which will let you run the <pretext/>-CLI without leaving the editor.
      </p>

      <p>
        To install, the editor, first download the installer from <url href="https://code.visualstudio.com/" visual="code.visualstudio.com">the VSCode website</url>.
      </p>

      <image width="70%" source="vscode-download.png">
        <description>Screenshot of the VSCode website, showing where to click to download the installer</description>
      </image>

      <p>
        When running the installer, be sure that the <q>Add to PATH</q> option is selected:
      </p>

      <image width="50%" source="vscode-setup.png">
        <description>Screenshot of the VSCode installer program, showing where to click to ensure the program is added to the Windows system environment variables</description>
      </image>

      <p>
        You should now have VSCode installed on your system.
      </p>
    </subsection>

    <subsection xml:id="windows-cli-python">
      <title>Python</title>
      <p>
        One difficulty with using <pretext /> on Windows is the fact that Python is not core software, and there are many different ways to install install.
        The recommended method for installing Python is to get it directly from <url href="https://www.python.org/" visual="python.org"/>.
        Other Python installations, such as Anaconda, or even Miniconda, include a lot of extras that we don't need.
      </p>

      <p>
        To install Python, simply download the installer from the <url href="https://www.python.org/" visual="python.org">Python website</url>.
      </p>

      <image width="70%" source="python-download.png">
        <description>Screenshot of the python.org webpage, showing where to access the installer download</description>
      </image>

      <p>
        When you run the installer, be sure to check off the box to add Python to the Windows PATH during installation.
        This will ensure that Python commands can be run from the command line without needing to provide the path to the Python program.
      </p>

      <image width="50%" source="python-setup.png">
        <description>Screenshot of the Python installer program, showing the box that needs to be checked to ensure it is added to the system environment variables</description>
      </image>
    </subsection>

    <subsection xml:id="windows-cli-git">
      <title>Git for Windows</title>
      <p>
        The next piece of software we need to install is Git for Windows.
        This will provide tools for allowing us to interact with textbook source on GitHub.
        More importantly, it provides us with the <term>Git Bash</term> terminal,
        which is what we will be running all of the commands for <pretext />.
      </p>

      <p>
        You can get Git for Windows at <url href="https://gitforwindows.org/" visual="gitforwindows.org"/>.
      </p>

      <p>
        The installation process for Git for Windows can seem quite complicated,
        as there are a lot of options, and many of them are quite technical.
        You can safely choose the defaults throughout, unless there is a particular setting you're familiar with that you wish to change.
        The only thing you might want to do is change the default editor.
        Since we have already installed VSCode, we can choose to use that instead of an editor like Emacs or Nano that you may be unfamiliar with.
      </p>

      <image width="50%" source="git-setup.png">
        <description>Screenshot of the Git for Windows installation program, showing how to select VSCode as the default text editor</description>
      </image>
    </subsection>

    <subsection xml:id="windows-cli-other-software">
      <title>Other software</title>

      <p>
        A number of additional programs may be needed to assist in processing your book, depending on what elements your book contains.
      </p>

      <p>
        <dl>
          <li>
            <title><latex/></title>
            <p>
              You will almost certainly need to be able to process <latex />, either to produce the <init>PDF</init> version of your book,
              or to process <latex /> images for the <init>HTML</init> version of your book.
            </p>

            <p>
              There are two ways to install <latex /> on Windows: <url href="https://miktex.org/" visual="miktex.org">MikTeX</url>,
              or <url href="https://www.tug.org/texlive/windows.html" visual="www.tug.org/texlive/windows.html">TeXLive</url>.
              Although TeXLive is the default <latex /> distribution for Linux and MacOS platforms,
              most Windows users find MikTeX easier to use, since it comes with package management software to assist with automatically installing needed <latex/> packages.
              One thing to keep in mind: with MikTeX, you <em>must</em> run an initial update from the MikTeX package manager before it will work correctly.
            </p>
          </li>
        </dl>
      </p>

      <sidebyside widths="33% 33% 33%">
        <image source="windows-path-1.png">
          <description>Screenshot of the Windows system property control panel, showing how to access the Environment Variables</description>
        </image>

        <image source="windows-path-2.png">
          <description>Screenshot of the Environment Variables control panel, showing how to access and edit the Path</description>
        </image>

        <image source="windows-path-3.png">
          <description>Screenshot of the interface for editing the Windows Path to add a new program</description>
        </image>
      </sidebyside>

      <p>
        <dl>
          <li>
            <title>Sage</title>
            <p>
              If your book includes Sage components, such as <c>sageplot</c> (but <em>not</em> Sage Cells),
              you will need to install Sage to process them.
              Sage is available at <url href="https://www.sagemath.org/" visual="www.sagemath.org"/>.
              Click on the download button, and follow the instructions in the installer.
            </p>
          </li>

          <li>
            <title>GitHub Desktop</title>
            <p>
              If you find it difficult to manage git from the command line,
              GitHub provides a graphical user interface for the Windows environment,
              called <url href="https://desktop.github.com/" visual="desktop.github.com">GitHub Desktop</url>.
              This provides a point-and-click interface for synchronizing your local changes with GitHub.
            </p>
          </li>
        </dl>
      </p>
    </subsection>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="windows-cli-installation">
    <title>Installing the CLI</title>

    <introduction>
      <p>
        You now have all the necessary software installed.
        Next, we need to set up Git Bash, and install the <pretext />-CLI.
      </p>
    </introduction>

    <subsection xml:id="windows-cli-git-setup">
      <title>Setting up Git Bash</title>
      <p>
        One change that you will want to make right away is setting the default working directory for Git Bash.
        In your home folder (<c>C:\Users\Sean</c> in our example), look for a file called <c>.bashrc</c>.
        If it doesn't already exist, open Git Bash, navigate to this folder, and type <c>touch .bashrc</c> to create the file.
        Open the file (it is a plain text file), and add the line <c>cd C:/Users/Sean</c>,
        where you should replace the directory with the one you want to use.
      </p>

      <p>
        Next, we need to set up <init>SSH</init> authentication, for more efficient communication with GitHub.
        We assume that you already have a GitHub account; it not, you should create one at <url href="https://github.com/" visual="github.com"/>.
        There are existing instructions available online at
        <url href="https://docs.github.com/en/authentication/connecting-to-github-with-ssh" visual="docs.github.com/en/authentication/connecting-to-github-with-ssh">docs.github.com</url>.
        To begin with, please follow the instructions provided there for generating an <init>SSH</init> key using Git Bash, and adding it to GitHub.
      </p>

      <p>
        There is one aspect of the instructions that is not quite correct.
        When you get to the step for <url href="https://docs.github.com/en/authentication/connecting-to-github-with-ssh/generating-a-new-ssh-key-and-adding-it-to-the-ssh-agent" visual="docs.github.com/en/authentication/connecting-to-github-with-ssh/generating-a-new-ssh-key-and-adding-it-to-the-ssh-agent">adding the ssh key to the ssh agent</url>,
        the instructions will tell you to add your <init>SSH</init> key to the <init>SSH</init> agent using a relative path, with a line such as <c>ssh-add ~/.ssh/id_ed25519</c>.
        <alert>You must use a full path here</alert>. Instead, type <c>ssh-add /c/Users/Sean/.ssh/id_ed25519</c>,
        where as usual you should replace <c>Users/Sean</c> with your own directory.
      </p>

      <p>
        There is one more step you will want to complete.
        The <c>ssh-agent</c> program will not start automatically when you open Git Bash.
        To change this, we follow the instructions provided at <url href="https://gist.github.com/bsara/5c4d90db3016814a3d2fe38d314f9c23" visual="gist.github.com/bsara/5c4d90db3016814a3d2fe38d314f9c23"/>.
      </p>

      <p>
        <ol>
          <li>
            <p>
              In the file <c>/c/Users/Sean/.ssh</c>, open the <c>config</c> file (or create it using the <c>touch</c> command in Git Bash if it doesn't already exist),
              and add the following lines:
              <cd>
                <cline>Host github.com</cline>
                <cline> Hostname github.com</cline>
                <cline> IdentityFile ~/.ssh/id_rsa</cline>
              </cd>
              Note that the second and third lines are indented by one space.
              Note also that this assumes an <init>RSA</init> key, but you may have chosen a different encryption method.
              You may, for example, want to replace <c>id_rsa</c> with <c>id_ed25519</c>.
            </p>
          </li>

          <li>
            <p>
              In the file <c>/c/Users/Sean/.bash_profile</c>, (again, create it if it does not already exist) add the following lines:
              <cd>
                <cline>test -f ~/.profile &amp;&amp; . ~/.profile</cline>
                <cline>test -f ~/.bashrc &amp;&amp; . ~/.bashrc</cline>
              </cd>
            </p>
          </li>

          <li>
            <p>
              In the file <c>/c/Users/Sean/.ssh</c>, we need to add the following script, which will automatically start the <c>ssh-agent</c>.
            </p>

            <program>
              <code>
                # Start SSH Agent
                #----------------------------

                SSH_ENV="$HOME/.ssh/environment"

                function run_ssh_env {
                  . "${SSH_ENV}" > /dev/null
                }

                function start_ssh_agent {
                  echo "Initializing new SSH agent..."
                  ssh-agent | sed 's/^echo/#echo/' > "${SSH_ENV}"
                  echo "succeeded"
                  chmod 600 "${SSH_ENV}"

                  run_ssh_env;

                  ssh-add ~/.ssh/id_rsa;
                }

                if [ -f "${SSH_ENV}" ]; then
                  run_ssh_env;
                  ps -ef | grep ${SSH_AGENT_PID} | grep ssh-agent$ > /dev/null || {
                    start_ssh_agent;
                  }
                else
                  start_ssh_agent;
                fi
              </code>
            </program>
          </li>
        </ol>
      </p>

      <p>
        You should now be set up to work with GitHub on your Windows machine.
        When you clone a GitHub repository containing a <pretext /> book, be sure to choose the <init>SSH</init> option rather than <init>HTML</init>.
      </p>
    </subsection>

    <subsection xml:id="windows-cli-install">
      <title>Installing the CLI</title>
      <p>
        Finally, we are ready to install the <pretext />-CLI. This is perhaps the easiest step of the whole process.
        From the Git Bash terminal, first type <c>which python</c> to confirm that Python has been successfully added to the PATH.
        You should see the path to your Python program if things are working correctly.
        If you don't, you may need to reinstall Python, or you can manually add it.
      </p>

      <p>
        To install the CLI, simply type <c>pip install pretext</c>.
      </p>

      <p>
        Congratulations! You are now ready to start using <pretext /> on your Windows machine.
        If you did not do so previously, there is one additional step you may want to take.
        In VSCode, go to File, then Preferences, then Extensions in the menu, or type <kbd>Ctrl</kbd>-<kbd>Shift</kbd>-X.
        In the search bar that comes up, type <q>pretext-tools</q>, and install the package that comes up.
        This will equip VSCode with syntax highlighting for <c>.ptx</c> files, as well as some automatic tag completion.
        (For example, typing <c>thm</c> and then the <kbd>Tab</kbd> key will automatically insert the <init>XML</init> markup for a theorem.)
      </p>

      <p>
        Additionally, from the command palette, (View, then Command Palette in the menu, or <kbd>Ctrl</kbd>-<kbd>Shift</kbd>-P)
        if you type <q>pretext</q>, you will see some built-in options for building your book using the CLI.
      </p>
    </subsection>
  </section>
</appendix>
