<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>

<!--   This file is part of the documentation of PreTeXt      -->
<!--                                                          -->
<!--      PreTeXt Author's Guide                              -->
<!--                                                          -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 2013-2016  Robert A. Beezer                -->
<!-- See the file COPYING for copying conditions.             -->

<appendix xml:id="windows-subsystem-linux">
    <title>Windows Subsystem for Linux</title>

    <p>
      Windows Subsystem for Linux is no longer the recommended method for Windows <pretext /> users.
      Instead, consider using either the web-based GitHub solution described in <xref ref="tutorial"/>
      or the handy <pretext />-CLI as discussed in <xref ref="processing-CLI"/>.
    </p>

    <p>
      <pretext /> developers who use
      Windows may be interested in the information in this appendix but do note that some information may be out of date.
    </p>

    <p>
    The <term>Windows Subsystem for Linux</term> (<init>WSL</init>)
    may be installed on computers running Windows 10.
    Several distributions of Linux are available.
    We will use  Ubuntu as an example; working with other distributions is quite similar.
    The latest news and announcements about <init>WSL</init> may be found at
    <url href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/commandline/wsl/about" visual="msdn.microsoft.com/commandline/wsl/about"/>.
    </p>

    <aside>
    <title> What is my OS build?</title>
    <p>
    An easy way to find your OS Build:
    Hold down the Windows key and R key simultaneously.
    Enter <c>winver.exe</c> in the resulting new window.
    The next window that opens will have the OS Build in small type near the top.
        </p>
    </aside>

    <paragraphs>
        <title>Installing WSL</title>
        <p>
	    If you have Windows 10 with OS Build greater than 16215 (August 2016),
        then installing <init>WSL</init> is not difficult. Just follow the
        (reasonably straightforward) instructions given by Microsoft at the address
        <url href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/commandline/wsl/install_guide" visual="msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/commandline/wsl/install_guide"/>.
        </p>
        <p>
        Upon completion of the installation, you should
        <ul>
        <li><p>be able to use the <c>bash</c> command from the <c>PowerShell</c> window,</p></li>
        <li><p>have your own <init>WSL</init> userid (distinct from Windows),</p></li>
        <li><p>have your own <init>WSL</init> password (distinct from Windows).</p></li>
        </ul>
        </p>
    </paragraphs>

    <aside>
        <title>A little background about using about the command line</title>

        <p>
        <ul>
        <li><p>
            You type in commands (terminated by the Enter key) and
            the operating system responds. For example, if you type in
            <c>date</c>, the
            operating system responds with (what it considers to be) the date.
            Using the command line is an ongoing conversation between you and
            the operating system.
        </p></li>
        <li><p>
            The <c>sudo</c> command:
            when a command starts with <c>sudo</c>, the rest of
            the command is executed with administrative privileges.
            This is needed, for example, to install software or
            update the operating system. You must give your
            password when you run <c>sudo</c> (although you get
            a little window of time after the first usage when
            it is not necessary to do so).
        </p></li>
        <li><p>
            The <c>sudo apt-get update</c> command: this is used to
            resynchronize the local listing of installed packages
            with those in the official repository.
        </p></li>
        <li><p>
            The <c>sudo apt-get upgrade</c> command: this is used to
            bring all the local software up to date with
            those in the official repository.
        </p></li>
        </ul>
        </p>
        <p>
        Run <c>sudo apt-get update</c> followed
        by <c>sudo apt-get upgrade</c> with a newly system to bring it
        up to date. It is a good idea to repeat this frequently to have
        the latest software on your computer.
        </p>
    </aside>

    <paragraphs>
        <title>Installing software</title>
        <p>
        The default configuration of <init>WSL</init> does not have the software needed
        for creating documents with <pretext/>.
        </p>
        <p>
        The program <term>xsltproc</term> is used to create your readable documents.
        It is installed with the command <c>sudo apt-get install xsltproc</c>.
        </p>
        <p>
         You are now ready to set up <pretext/>.
        </p>
    </paragraphs>

    <paragraphs>
        <title>Putting <pretext/> on your computer</title>
        <p>
        Here are the steps necessary to get the <pretext/> software onto
        your computer:
        <ul>
        <li><p>Make a new directory <c>mkdir pretext</c></p></li>
        <li><p>Make your own clone of the <pretext/> repository
            <c>git clone https://github.com/PreTeXtBook/pretext.git</c></p></li>
        <li><p>Move to the new directory <c>cd pretext</c></p></li>
        <li><p>Initialize the new directory with <c>git pull</c></p></li>
        </ul>
        This last command synchronizes your files with those in the official repository.
        You should run it frequently to keep your files up to date.
        </p>
    </paragraphs>

    <paragraphs>
        <title>The simplest example</title>
        <p>
        Here is a brief description of the use of <init>WSL</init> to create
        readable files.
        You, as the author, create the <init>xml</init> file.
        The system will contain an appropriate <init>xsl</init> file that translates
        your <init>xml</init> file to something readable.
        </p>
        <p>
        Several editors come with <init>WSL</init> by default including
        <init>nano</init>, <init>pico</init>, <init>vi</init>,  and <init>vim</init>.
        In addition, editing is possible using <init>notebook.exe</init>.
        Here are the steps to follow:
        <ol>
        <li>
        <p>
        Type the command <c>cd</c> to align yourself in your home directory.
        </p>
        </li>
        <li><p>
            Use one of the editors to create a file called <c>hw.xml</c>
            (you could use the command <c>nano hw.xml</c>), and add
            the following text:
            <cd>
            &lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;
            &lt;pretext&gt;
                &lt;article xml:id="hw"&gt;
                &lt;p&gt;Hello, World!&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/article&gt;
            &lt;/pretext&gt;
            </cd></p>
        </li>
        <li><p>
            Run the command
            <c>xsltproc pretext/xsl/pretext-html.xsl hw.xml</c>
            Upon completion, your should have a file called <c>hw.html</c>.
        </p></li>
        <li><p>
            You now want to view the <c>hw.html</c> file in a browser,
	    This is done with the command <c>explorer.exe hw.html</c>.
        </p></li>
        </ol>
        The <c>edit-xsltproc-view</c> cycle just given may seem daunting at first blush.
        Some things that can help:
        <ul>
        <li><p>
            Pressing the up arrow when at the command line displays the previously
            executed commands.  Hitting the enter key while such a command is displayed
            executes it. This saves a lot of retyping.
        </p></li>
        <li><p>
            It is possible to define aliases to shorten commands. Your local Linux guru can
            show how this is done.
        </p></li>
        <li><p>
            It is possible to define scripts to shorten multiple commands.
            Your local Linux guru can show how this is done.
        </p></li>
        </ul>
        </p>
    </paragraphs>

</appendix>
