<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!--   This file is part of the documentation of PreTeXt      -->
<!--                                                          -->
<!--      PreTeXt Author's Guide                              -->
<!--                                                          -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 2013-2023  Robert A. Beezer                -->
<!-- See the file COPYING for copying conditions.             -->

<chapter xml:id="tutorial">
    <title>Getting Started Tutorial</title>

    <introduction>
      <p>
        This chapter serves as a tutorial for quickly getting started with <pretext /> in your web browser
        using the free <url href="https://github.com/features/codespaces">GitHub Codespaces service</url>.
        (Advanced users who'd prefer to install our free and open-source software
        to their own machine may choose to skip ahead to <xref ref="quickstart-example"/>.)
      </p>
      <objectives>
        <introduction><p>At the end of this tutorial you will have...</p></introduction>
        <ul>
          <li><p>Created a free GitHub account.</p></li>
          <li><p>Created a GitHub Codespace for authoring <pretext/> in your web browser.</p></li>
          <li><p>Learned the first steps to editing a <pretext/> document.</p></li>
          <li><p>Converted your document to both <m>\LaTeX</m> and accessible HTML.</p></li>
          <li><p>Deployed your HTML to the web.</p></li>
        </ul>
      </objectives>
      <p>
        The community does its best to keep this guide updated, but for even more up-to-date advice,
        join us at our regular Zoom drop-ins announced at
        <url href="https://groups.google.com/g/pretext-announce/">our Google group</url> or
        watch a recording posted in <xref ref="tutorial-videos"/>.
      </p>
    </introduction>

    <section xml:id="tutorial-github">
      <title>Using GitHub and Codespaces</title>
      <subsection>
        <title>GitHub</title>
        <p>
          <term>GitHub</term> is a freely-available service for authoring, sharing, and deploying
          documents and source code, owned by Microsoft. It uses the free and open-source <term>Git</term>
          software for version management.
        </p>
        <p>
          There are other services such as <url href="https://cocalc.com">CoCalc</url>
          (see <xref ref="topic-build-in-cocalc"/>) and
          <url href="https://about.gitlab.com/">GitLab</url> for managing <pretext/> documents
          online, as well as other ways to write <pretext/> that don't require anything
          besides installing the free and open-source <pretext/> software onto your own device
          (see <xref ref="quickstart-example"/> to learn more).
        </p>
        <p>
          We will use GitHub's service for this tutorial as it the most popular way to share and disseminate
          <pretext/> documents, and provides the easiest pathway to getting started writing in the 
          <pretext/> language.
        </p>
        <p>
          To create your free GitHub account,
          <url href="https://github.com/signup">
              follow the instructions on GitHub's
              signup page
          </url>. You can also log into an existing GitHub account if you already have one.
          Be sure to note your GitHub username and password in your password manager
          (or however you usually keep track of login credentials).
        </p>
        <p>
          Educators and non-profit researchers can get many of GitHub's paid features
          for free. While this is not strictly required for the rest of the tutorial, it's a
          useful way to avoid GitHub's limit on free Codespaces usage.
        </p>
        <p>
          Apply at
          <url href="https://education.github.com/discount_requests/pack_application">Education.GitHub.com</url>
          to unlock these features (in our experience, applications are usually processed quickly for <c>.edu</c>
          email addresses).
        </p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection>
        <title>Codespaces</title>
        <p>
          A <term>Codespace</term> is an authoring environment that lives in the <q>cloud</q>,
          that is, a virtual machine hosted by GitHub that has all of the software needed to
          create great accessible documents, accessible with just your web browser.
        </p>
        <p>
          This coding environment uses a web version of Virtual Studio
          Code, an open-source text editor, along with the PreTeXt community's
          custom plugins and software to get started authoring quickly.
        </p>
        <p>
          Follow the instructions at <url href="https://github.com/PreTeXtBook/pretext-codespace" />
          to get started. You'll have the option to make your work public (recommended if you want
          support from the rest of the <pretext/> community) or private.
        </p>
        <p>
          Either way, this is a one-time process. Take note of the URL your new repository lives at
          (something like <c>https://github.com/user-name/repository-name</c>) so you can find it
          the next time you want to work on your project.
          Then you'll be ready for <xref ref="tutorial-first-document"/>.
        </p>
      </subsection>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="tutorial-first-document">
      <title>Your First PreTeXt Document</title>
      <subsection>
        <title>Building for web</title>
        <p>
          Inside the VS Code window you opened through Codespaces, open <c>main.ptx</c>.
          You can build your entire project in a few different ways.
          <ul>
            <li>
              <p>
                Click the green triangle in the top-right corner of the window
                (hovering will show <c>Build (select target)</c>).  A window will pop
                up asking for a <term>target</term> to build: choose <q>web</q>.
              </p>
            </li>
            <li>
              <p>
                In the <q>Explorer</q> panel on the left-hand side of the window,
                you can expand the <q>PreTeXt Commands</q> menu and select the
                <c>Build default target</c> option, or the <c>Build ...</c> option
                and choose <c>web</c>.
              </p>
            </li>
            <li>
              <p>
                You can use the keyboard shortcut <kbd>CTRL</kbd>+<kbd>ALT</kbd>+<kbd>b</kbd>
                (replacing <kbd>CTRL</kbd> with <kbd>CMD</kbd> if you have a Mac).
              </p>
            </li>
          </ul>
          The resulting HTML files will be available in the <c>output/web</c> directory of your project.
        </p>

        <figure xml-id="tutorial-figure-codespaces-pretext">
          <caption>PreTeXt commands in Codespaces</caption>
          <image width="50%" source="codespaces-pretext.png">
            <description>Screenshot of VS Code PreTeXt palette in Codespaces</description>
          </image>
        </figure>
      </subsection>

      <subsection xml:id="tutorial-previewing">
        <title>Viewing</title>
        <p>
          You can preview these HTML files you just built using the <term>View</term> command.
          Again, you can access this in multiple ways: top-right icon or PreTeXt Commands menu.
          When you use either of these, you may be given options on how to view the document,
          depending on what VS Code plugins you have available to you. Try one or another until
          you're able to view your web build in either a new tab of your browser or a tab within
          VS Code.
        </p>

        <p>
          Now is a great time to try to make edits to your source files (maybe change the title).
          Note that these changes aren't updated live in your preview:
          you will need to build again, and then refresh the preview window to see them.
        </p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection xml:id="tutorial-pdf">
        <title>Building <m>\LaTeX</m> and PDF</title>
        <p>
          The instructions above can be repeated to produce <m>\LaTeX</m> code:
          just choose <c>print-latex</c> instead of <c>web</c> as your target.
          The resulting files are available in <c>output/print-latex</c>.
        </p>
        <p>
          Of course, it'd be even more convenient to produce a PDF directly.
          This requires software that can process <m>\LaTeX</m>, which is not installed
          in the <pretext/> Codespace by default. This can be accomplished by copy-pasting
          the following line into a <q>terminal</q> and pressing <kbd>Enter</kbd> to run
          the command. (Use <kbd>Ctrl</kbd>+<kbd>`</kbd> to make
          a terminal appear below the text editor if it's not already on screen.)
        </p>
        <program language="bash">
          <input>
            sudo bash ./.devcontainer/postCreateCommand.sh
          </input>
        </program>
        <p>
          After everything is installed, repeat the above instructions
          with the <c>print</c> target to produce a PDF. It can be downloaded by right-clicking
          <c>output/print/main.pdf</c> in the VS Code file explorer, or previewed using
          a View command.
        </p>
        <p>
          Alternatively, the next time you create a Codespace, you can click the three dots next to the
          <c>+</c> and select the <q>devcontainer</q> that has <q>pretext-full</q> in its name.
        </p>
        <p>
          In any case, once you install this software once, you should be good to go as long as your
          Codespace exists.
        </p>
      </subsection>


      <subsection xml:id="tutorial-saving">
        <title>Saving your work</title>
        <p>
          Using Codespaces will keep all your files <q>in the cloud</q> on GitHub's server,
          saved automatically as you edit.
          As long as your Codespace is active, your files will be saved there
          for your private use.
        </p>

        <p>
          However, you will want to periodically <term>commit &amp; sync</term> these files to your
          <term>git repository</term> on GitHub (located on the web somewhere like
          <c>https://github.com/user-name/repository-name</c>).
          This creates a backup of your work, and has the added benefit of
          allowing collaborators (not to mention members of the PreTeXt community who watch
          the <url href="https://groups.google.com/g/pretext-support">PreTeXt-support</url>
          Google group) to access your files as well.
        </p>

        <p>
          While Git and GitHub have a lot of features, fortunately there's a very simple way to use them
          via Codespaces. As you edit files, you'll notice that their filenames will turn orange, and new
          files will appear green. Likewise, a blue number will appear in the left sidebar.
        </p>

        <figure xml-id="tutorial-figure-codespaces-sidebar">
          <caption>Filenames changing color as they are edited in Codespaces</caption>
          <image width="50%" source="codespaces-sidebar.png">
            <description>Screenshot of VS Code sidebar in Codespaces</description>
          </image>
        </figure>

        <p>
          This blue badge is next to the Source Control view.
          You will notice a list of files that were changed;
          you can click on any of these to see what the changes are.
        </p>

        <figure xml-id="tutorial-figure-codespaces-diff">
          <caption>A <q>Git diff</q> showing changes in a file</caption>
          <image width="100%" source="codespaces-diff.png">
            <description>Screenshot of VS Code Git diff in Codespaces</description>
          </image>
        </figure>

        <p>
          <em>Type a message describing the changes you've made</em> then
          click the green <q>Commit and Sync</q> button. If it just says <q>Commit</q>,
          use the drop-down menu to choose <q>Commit and Sync</q>.
        </p>

        <figure xml-id="tutorial-figure-codespaces-sync">
          <caption>Commiting and syncing changes</caption>
          <image width="50%" source="codespaces-sync.png">
            <description>Screenshot of VS Code source control in Codespaces</description>
          </image>
        </figure>

        <p>
          To see that this is successful, return to <url href="https://github.com"/> (your
          Codespace lives at <c>github.dev</c>), then find your public repository page
          where you first created the Codespace. You should see your files with all your
          committed/synced changes. (That is, most of them: many files, such as log files and
          temporary build files, are not tracked by Git. This is no problem: they are created
          during a build automatically and don't need to be saved or shared with others.)
        </p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection xml:id="tutorial-generate">
        <title>Generating assets</title>

        <p>
          If your document contains certain elements, you might need to <term>generate</term> their assets
          for use in certain output formats. Depending on your build target, these include:
          <ul>
            <li><tag>latex-image</tag></li>
            <li><tag>sagemath</tag></li>
            <li><tag>asymptote</tag></li>
            <li><tag>youtube</tag></li>
            <li><tag>webwork</tag></li>
            <li><tag>codelens</tag></li>
          </ul>
        </p>

        <p>
          You can generate assets in much the same way you run a build,
          though you may need to first install the extra software as described in
          <xref ref="tutorial-pdf"/>. After that is done, you can use
          the button on the top-right of the window, the option in the <q>PreTeXt Commands</q> menu,
          or the keyboard shortcut <kbd>CTRL</kbd>+<kbd>ALT</kbd>+<kbd>g</kbd>.
        </p>

      </subsection>

      <subsection xml:id="tutorial-deploy">
        <title>Deploy</title>
        <p>
          So you have worked tirelessly to prepare course notes or a book, built and previewed,
          synced changes to your git repository, and now you are ready to share the results of
          your efforts with the world.  It's time to <term>deploy</term> your project!
        </p>

        <p>
          With our Codespace setup this is simple.  From the <q>PreTeXt Commands</q> menu, click on
          <q>Deploy to GitHub</q>.  This will automatically take the most recent build of your web target
          and host it through <url href="https://pages.github.com/">GitHub Pages</url>.  Watch the output
          pane for a link to your published site; unlike the preview link you've been using on <c>github.dev</c>
          that's private to only you, this <c>github.io</c> link is ready to share with the world.
          (It can take a few minutes for the site to get set up
          or updated; there should be another link to view the progress of the GitHub <q>action</q> that
          reports the progress.)
        </p>
      </subsection>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="tutorial-videos">
      <title>Videos</title>

      <p>A series of videos showcasing how to get started with PreTeXt
      as the ecosystem evolves over time is curated by
      <url href="https://clontz.org">Steven Clontz</url>. Roughly once
      a month, a <q>Getting Started with PreTeXt Today</q> presentation is
      made available on Zoom, showcasing any new workflows or technologies
      that are best recommended for writing modern PreTeXt. These videos
      are documented here for your reference.</p>

      <figure xml:id="gsv-2023-jan">
          <caption>Getting Started in 2023 Jan</caption>
          <video xml:id="gsv-2023-jan-video" youtube="y-33Ube-Rhk"/>
      </figure>
    </section>

  <section xml:id="quickstart-example">
    <title>For Advanced Users New to PreTeXt</title>

    <p>
      This section is intended for users who have read
      <xref ref="start-here"/>
      and are already experienced
      with other open-source software projects. If you're more
      interested in a browser-based workflow to getting started with
      PreTeXt, check out <xref ref="tutorial-github"/>.
    </p>

    <p>
      PreTeXt is an open-source
      <url href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/XML">XML</url> language
      primarily powered by
      <url href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/XSLT">XSLT</url> and
      <url href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Python_(programming_language)">Python</url>
      tools.
    </p>

    <p>
      For new authors working on the commandline who want to use their
      favorite text editor or IDE, we recommend <c>pip install</c>ing the PreTeXt-CLI
      from the Python Package Index. <xref ref="processing-CLI"/> has these details,
      and <c>pretext -h</c> and <c>pretext CMD -h</c> are at your disposal as well
      after installation.
    </p>

    <p>
      Some context for experienced Python developers: PreTeXt development is primarily
      split over two GitHub repositories:
      <url href="https://github.com/PreTeXtBook/pretext">PreTeXtBook/pretext</url>
      for the <q>core</q> functionality of PreTeXt, and the more recent
      <url href="https://github.com/PreTeXtBook/pretext-cli">PreTeXtBook/pretext-cli</url>
      that packages up these resources into a Python package with several UX enhancements
      such as a simplified command line interface and project management that does not require
      the use of custom makefiles.
    </p>

    <p>
      If you're interested in potentially contributing back to PreTeXt someday, please
      feel free to request to join
      <url href="https://groups.google.com/g/pretext-dev">our developer Google Group</url>
      and say hello!
    </p>
  </section>
</chapter>
